<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The passoinate [sic] morrice]</title>
            <author>A., fl. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851000</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851000</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16252</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16252)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1675:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The passoinate [sic] morrice]</title>
                  <author>A., fl. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by R. Bourne? for Richard Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption on leaf B1r; imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Author's preface signed: A.</note>
                  <note>Continues the text of STC 23867.5: Tell-trothes new-yeares gift beeing Robin Good-fellowes newes.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The passionate morrice.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:1"/>
            <p>The Paſsionate Morrice.</p>
            <p>London, Imprinted by Richard Jones. 1593.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:2"/>
            <head>To the Gentlewomen and others of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Nce more (moſt beautiful damſels) I am bold to preſume of your won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fauour, thereby being lead to a performance of a vowed duetie, where a kinde zeale bindeth to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the acceptance of a ſeruiceable good will, there a carefull feate that forewarneth to incurre the hazard of offence, maketh the hart to ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger betweene hope and deſpaire: hoping through the kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your gentle diſpoſitions, to obtaine a defence againſt iniurious cauillers, and fearing by an ouer-bolde preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to offer offence to the affable ſweetenes of your ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne curteſie. But ſeeing my deſire to bee poſſeſſed of the better cordiall, makes me hart-ſtrong to ſuppe of that poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is likeſt to lengthen my welfare, the ſame being an aſſured confidence of your continuall carefulnes, in ſhrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with your affection the ſlender ſubſtance of my humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Morrice.</p>
            <p>It is not long ſince for <hi>Tel-troths</hi> Newyeeres-gift, I preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto your liking <hi>Robin good-fellow</hi> his newes, with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiue againſt Loues moſt iniurious enemie Ielouſie: which though it was a token to gratifie the day, yet if with indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iudgement the matter therein contained be conſidered of, I doubt not, though it was a New-yeeres day toy, it may proue a many yeeres helpe to hinder that hagges enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. The worke tooke his title according to the time of his creation but ſhall <hi>Robins</hi> preſcriptions be followed; the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients maladie ſhall continually finde it a gifte to ſignifie the
<pb facs="tcp:16252:3"/> good beginning and proſperous proceeding of many new yeeres vnto them. But now to ſend <hi>Tell-troth</hi> packing, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie</hi> hath thruſt himſelfe into your ſeruice, who though at the firſt ſight he may ſeeme a crabbed companion, yet let me beſeech you to ſtay your cenſure til you haue throughly tryed what is in him, and if then he ſhewes not himſelfe a diligent pleaſer of your immortal vertues, memorize in the Cronicles of Diſdaine the ſame of that runnagate ſimplicitie, and let me for his faulte be baniſhed from your good thoughts to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ignominie.</p>
            <p>I was rather deſirous to trauel altogether inuiſible, then to haue had a title which might giue light to the vnderſtanding of me your vnworthie profeſſed Author; but ſince the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers denie me that priuiledge, I am content to ſubiect my ſelf to the opinions of courteous diſpoſitions: beſeeching you to beare with my vaine, for that the vanitie of this age regardes no other, nor would any be content to heare of faultes, vnleſſe they be tolde them in meriment. I proteſt there is nothing ſcandalous therein, nor which is ment to offer iniury to any, onely my purpoſe is, that if you ſhould know any like vnto any of thoſe in diſpoſition, that either you forewarne them thoſe monſtrous iniurious vices, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of them as peſtilent fooliſh wretches. To ſhun tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, I commit m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intention to your miſticall conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, my woorke to your courteous protection, my ſelfe to your fauourable opinions, and your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſelues to the heauens tuition.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in ſeruice and affection moſt loyall <hi>A.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:3"/>
            <head>THE PASSOINATE Morrice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the moneth of <hi>March,</hi> a time as fit for wooing as <hi>May</hi> is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to ſporte in, <hi>Honeſtie</hi> trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as his cuſtome is, to ſearch ſuch corners as good fellowſhip h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unteth, it was my hap, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into <hi>Hogſden,</hi> to light vpon a houſe, wherein were met ſuch a troupe of louers, as had not the hall béen wondrous bigge, a multitude ſhould haue béen forced to ſtand without dores. Yet though the roume was ſo ſpatious, as an armie might haue lodged therein with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out peſterment, notwithſtanding it was ſo well filled at this inſtant, as all the place <hi>Honeſtie</hi> could get amongſt them, was to ſit on the rafters on the top of the houſe, which fitted beſt my humour, that deſires rather to ſée then to be ſéene. There ſeated in my Maieſtie (as ready to heare newes, as the pick thanke is forward to tell newes) I might eaſely perceaue my louers mated, as if they ment to make Marche birds, euery man hauing his ſwéete hart, and euery couple their corner. There were of all ſortes, and in many manners ſorted, ſome batchelers ſewed to widdowes, others to maides, widdowers likewiſe wooed ſome maides, and otherſome widdowes, there was age and youth coupled together, equalitie of yeares courting each other, and diuerſity of diſpoſitions, arguing to make a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:4"/>
            <p> Amongſt them, I lent my eares firſt to a couple that had choſen forth the moſt ſecret corner in the houſe, which were not worſt fitted for yeares; for it was a youth of thrée and twentie, that had matched himſelfe with a maide of eightéene: hée holding her vpon his knée, with his right hand claſping hers, &amp; his left about her mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, made many proffers to win her fauour, and breathed many ſighes to ſhew his loue, he vowed conſtancie with proteſtations, and confirmed with othes the pleadge of his loyaltie; he ſhewed her how long he had loued her befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he durſt tel her of his affection, how many iournies he had made with loſſe of labour, and how many complaintes to the God of Loue not finding any remedie. Hée made her priuie to the many houres he had at ſundrie times ſpent in watching to haue a ſight of her, ſhewing vnto her how ioyfull he were, had he, perchance, but ſeene any creature belonging to her fathers houſe, yea were it but the little dog that turned the ſpit. Many times (quoth he) haue I lookt vp to the windowe, imagining I haue ſéene thy picture engrauen in the glaſſe, when with long gaſing to viewe the true portrature thereof, I haue at laſt recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led my ſelfe, by letting my ſoule ſée how mine eyes were deceiued, in expecting that true forme from the glaſſe, which was onely pictured in my heart. Then would I ſorrowe to my ſelfe, and power forth ſuch paſſions into the ayre, as my heart, bring ouer loaded with the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie they would force, would conſtraine me to ſit downe, ending my ſpéeche with ſuch ſighes, as my breathed ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe would no leſſe darken the ayre, then a miſtie fogge doth obſcure the ſkie. But at laſt, comming to my ſelfe, I would returne home, locking vp my ſelfe within my lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, a cloſe priſoner by the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of loue; where to paſſe away the time, I would write paſſionate lines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous ditties, pleaſing fancies, pleaſant rounddelaies, and dolefull drerelayes. Now would I thinke to winne thée by letters, anon I thought it better to pen ſpéeches, but ſuddainely, both miſliking mée, I would throwe
<pb facs="tcp:16252:4"/> my ſelfe vppon the bed, ſo long thinking which way to obtaine thée, as in the end I ſhould fall into a ſlumber. Yet amidſt my reſt, my thoughtes concerning thée were reſtles: For then ſhould I dreame ſometimes thou ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt me faire, repaying my kindenes with ſwéete kiſſes, granting my requeſts and forward to doe my will: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waking from forth that ſoueraigne eluſion, looking to finde thée, I ſhould féele the bed-poaſtes, that hard hap, turning my glad heart to a new bread ſorrow, which was the more painefull, by how much my dreame was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: at another time, I ſhould thinke, that ſuing to thée for ſauour, thou wouldeſt beſtowe frownes, &amp; profering my ſeruice, thou wouldſt offer ſkornes. If I ſighed, thou wouldſt ſmile, laughing at my teares, and ioying at my griefe, requiting euery kinde demande with ſo cruell an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, as if thy bitter words could not force me to leaue my ſuite, thy ſkornefull farewels ſhould fruſtrate my wil: offering to touch thine hand, mée thought thou profereds thy foote, and ſtouping to catch that, being glad of any thing, thou wouldſt in a rage fling from me, and leaue the doore barred againſt me. There ſhould I ſit till my téeth chattered in my head, and my heart aked in my bellie: then ſhould I ſhake for colde, and ſigh for ſorrowe, when thinking to knock my legges againſt the ground to get heate, I ſhould kick al the cloathes off me, being in the end conſtrained to awake through colde. At what time that colde fare would better content me, then the former flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering cheare did pleaſe me, being as glad it was falſe, as I would haue béen glad if the other had béen true. Many like to theſe did I endure before my acquaintance with thée, not knowing any meanes how to obtaine the ſame of thée, vntill happely finding thee in a ſommers euening at the dore, I preſumed to enter parlie with thée, offering my ſelfe your ſeruant, which had béen a tweluemoneth your ſworne ſubiect, doubting of your patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, though you ſéeme to be a patterne of pittie. How and after what order I haue ſince that time beſought your ſauour, your ſelfe ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:16252:5"/> be my iudge, for I liſt not to rehearſe my dayly ſhiftes, to ſhewe my zeale, my manyfolde concluſions to obtaine your companie, my giftes to wooe the ſeruants, and my preſents to gaine your good will. But to be briefe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to come to that I like beſt, one whole yeare I loued thée before thou kneweſt me, &amp; thrée more are paſſed ſince firſt I ſpake to thée: yet then was I as neare as now I am, and now as farre off as I was then. Say therefore ſwéete, ſince to ſtay longer yéelds but little comfort, ſhall my ſuite now end with the verdit, You loue me?</p>
            <p>To which long preamble, ſhut vp with ſo whot a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, ſhe no leſſe prepared herſelfe to anſwere him, then Frier <hi>Tuck</hi> vſed ceremonies before he ſong mattens. She caſt her eyes vp to Heauen, as if ſhe had béen making her praiers to loue, ſighing ſo bitterly, as I thought hir plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket lace would haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then to the matter thus ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. Alas gentle ſir, I muſt confeſſe I haue found you kinde, and you haue béen at a great deale more coſt then I could wiſh you had, your ſuite hath béen long, and my kindenes not much, nor doe I hope you e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pect more at my hands then you haue had, before my friends haue gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their good will. Maidens are modeſt, and muſt not bée prodigall of their courteſie: children are bound and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent without their parents counſell: pardon mée therefore I pray you, if I ſay I loue you not, ſince my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowes you not, and thinke not much if I deſire you to leaue to loue mée, vntill my mother giue me leaue to like of you. At which time aſſure your ſelfe I will bee as ready to performe your will, as they ſhall be forward to wiſh me that good, and thus in the meane time, I hope you will reſt ſatiſfied. This was a ſhroade bone for my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate youth to gnawe on, that being ſo ſtrucken on the head as his heart aked therewith, thought to eaſe his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe with this replie. Ah my ſwéeteſt ſwéete (quoth hée) Thinke not on thy fathers counſel, ſéeing a greater friend craueth his deſerte, nor let me reſt their leaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pitie, that hath thus long remained conſtant vnto
<pb facs="tcp:16252:5"/> thée. I loue thée nor for thy fréendes ſake, though I loue them for thy ſake: nor doe thou lothe me for their pleaſure that liues but at thy pleaſure. But ſwéete and ſoueraigne of my hart, as thy thoughts be not tied to their wils, ſo let not thy loue be linked ſo faſt to their liking, as their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſhould end my life by remouing thy loue. Say my god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, and therewithall as he was procéeding, ſhe cut off the reſt with this ſhort anſwere. I beſéech you ſir to leaue off your courting, vnleſſe you entend ſome other concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then as yet I can gather: for of my faith loue you I wil not, nor conſent I dare not without my fréends giue their conſents firſt, and thereupon ſhe thruſted through the throng and poaſted out of doores, leauing my paſſionate louer to ſay his pater noſter alone, where we will leaue them.</p>
            <p>What I thought I will tell you, and I hope you will not doubt of the matter, for that <hi>Honeſtie</hi> ſpeakes it. One yéeres loue without acquaintance, and thrée yéeres ſuite to be neuer the néerer: either he was a bad lawyer, or ſhe a monſtrous vniuſt iudge: but be it, both a paſſionate Aſſe, and a péeuiſh wench were well met. But marke his folly and her cunning, he building Caſtles in the aire and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting trappes in the Sunne to catch the ſhadowe of a coye queane, was pleaſed by her, with wagging his bawble, and ringing his bell, while ſhe pickt his pocket and cut his purſſe. A proper péece of ſeruice of a paſſionate Souldier, and a prettie ſleight of a flattering Slut: I would we had more of them, nay why wiſh I that, ſince the worlde is too full of ſuch alreadie? Yet of my honeſty, ſhe was as fitte a match for ſuch a foole, as might be found in the worlde. A great deale of fond fancie repaied with a ſharpe ſhorte deniall, and thrée yéeres affection rewarded with an ounce of flatterie, mingled with a pound of diſcurteſie? a good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall to comfort ſo kinde a hart. Oh the ſubtilty of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, that vnder the ſhadow of obedience, couers y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> craft of coſonage. It is hotte loue that buildes on fréendes liking, and peſtilent affection that relies rather on the mothers
<pb facs="tcp:16252:6"/> loue, then on the Louers loyaltie. Such as ſtands ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly on their Parents good will, hauing dealt ſo craftily without their conſent, are worthie by <hi>Honeſties</hi> doome to ſtand in a Cage, vntill either their fréends good will be got, or her ſwéet harts licence obtained for her deliuerie. And this is too good, for that the kinde Aſſe wil too too ſoone releaſe her: I thinke this puniſhment would be worſe welcome vnto her, namely, that ſhe be bound from mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, ſo long as ſhe hath kept him without his anſwere, which will ſo pinche her prodigall deſire, as either ſhe will forſweare honeſtie, or neuer commit the like knauerie. Oh there is a companie of minions which delight to haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſutors, that they may bragge amongſt their mates of their diuerſitie of louers: they thinke it commendable to haue ſtore of cuſtomers. But knewe they ſo much as I know, they were better to goe once in a fortnight to <hi>Greenes</hi> Cunnyberries, then to haue ſuch reſorte to haunt their companies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honeſtie</hi> honours the conſent of Parents, but abhorres ſuch loue as is built on their liking, if there be no remedie but that either they ſhall like, or thou wilt not loue, let him haue thy Fathers good will before he obtaines thy countenance: for doubtles ſhe that will entertaine lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and repay their courting with kindenes, will care as little for her fréends counſell, hapning on a mate ſhe can fancie, as the horſe wil for haye, that hath his manger full of prouender. And what is the cauſe why ſo many ſtande ſo curiouſly on their fréends conſent? nought for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, but the preſumption of a double baite, that being ſure of their countenance, they may be aſſured of an other din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner if their owne likes them not; or otherwiſe to haue a hole to hide a For in, for that her owne denne is not ſecret enough. If her Huſband controlle her for any miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or reproue her of any diſhoneſt behauiour, then on goes her pantoples, building the reckoning of her honeſty on her fathers countenance, ſo far preſuming of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den duetie for the match making, as if he kept the keye of
<pb facs="tcp:16252:6"/> her huſwiferie. Her long toung vtters large ſpéeches, ſtanding at defiance vnder the banner of her Fathers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and his houſe muſt be her Caſtell to kéepe her from her Huſband. This is the commoditie a man ſhall reap by ſuch a match, and this is their meaning that would couer their rebellion with the cloak of obedience. Is not he wel preferred that is ſo well married, and how can he mend it? Marry no way but this, that he which is mated with the like inconuenience, to learne more wit againſt the next time, ſtriuing in the meane time to pleaſe both her and her fréends, ſince he had ſo much reaſon to woo both her fréends and her to be bound to ſo bad a bargaine.</p>
            <p>It is follie (quoth a wiſe man) to be ſorrowful for things irrecouerable, and <hi>Honeſtie</hi> thinkes it madnes to repent for déedes done, whereof her ſelfe is culpable: can any man be ſo witles (eſpecially in matter wherein wiſedome is ſo much required) as to doe, and wiſh vndoone in a moment? yea d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ubtles, <hi>Honeſtie</hi> knowes ſuch, they being the hotte ſpurres of our age, that thinke euery day a twelue moneth vntill they be married, and after they are matched, euery houre ſeauen yéeres, vntill they are parted. It was hotte loue that will be ſo ſoone colde, ſome of you will ſay, but I ſay, if it bad béen hot loue (as it was burning luſt) it would not haue béen ſo ſoone colde. For whereas y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> prouerb goes, that <hi>hot loue wil be ſoone colde,</hi> it is ment by ſuch affection as wants matter therby to continue longer. For as that is the pureſt wood which yéelds the perfecteſt heat, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer it is, the ſooner it wilbe it own deſtruction, leauing the ſitters by without fire, vnles a freſh ſupply be as néede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, added; ſo wil our hotte loue (whoſe kindled affection is come vnto it perfection, the hart being on ſuch a blaze, as euery part of it is on a light flame) decay (as reaſon and nature requireth) vnles new faggots of kindenes, adde freſh matter for fiering, the ſupply thereof remoning all ſuſpition of want of affection. How pure y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> loue is, where there is ſo light a regarde of proffered kindenes, as my Fathers will or my Mothers leaue muſt be a Spurre
<pb facs="tcp:16252:7"/> to my liking, let euery one iudge that knowes loue.</p>
            <p>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n my opinion, as I confeſſe that the duetie we owe to our Parents, may doo muche where the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof bindes to obeye, ſo muſt I confirme that loue is a duetie himſelfe, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nding to ſo great obedience and tying with ſuch ſtrong conuaiances, as he remoues all thoughts of lower dueties: I tearming al dueties lower, for that by commaundement thoſe dueties muſt be reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in reſpect of the louing duetie that a Huſband ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Now how far my nice Mimon was from knowing this duetie, her coye demeanour and cunning behauiour hath manifeſted. Yet how happie was my youth at l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt to be rid of ſuch a monſter? And monſter may I tearme her in reſpect of her lewde behauiour; for was it not much better that her inconſtancie ſhould haue béene knowen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was faſt linked vnto her, then it ſhould haue béene found when it had béen incurable? Doubtles it was a good cauſe he had to double his oriſons vnto loue, for ſo louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſeruing him from ſo peſtilent a prittie-bird, I ſhould haue ſaid pricking-burre, or paultry bauble.</p>
            <p>BVt to come to my ſecond couple, which were ſeated op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to theſe in an other corner, being a luſtie wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dower that was courting a gallant wench, both of them being highly beholding to nature for her liberall ſkill in their making, which were thus placed. She was ſet down ouerlooked by him ſtanding before her, hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne of his hands leaning on her lap, and the other reſting on the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, hauing therby (as I geſſe) the more libertie to vſe his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in beſtowing kinde kiſſes and louing fauours: ſo he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeated, and thus he began to ſue. Faire Maide (quoth he) I know my experience to be greater then your practiſe, for that I haue tried, rules me by reaſon: hauing loued and liued with my loue, vntill by the fates I was bere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of that fruit, ſo well liked I of my laſt loſſe, as my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer good hap bréeds an aſſured hope of the like good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that being a helpe to further my will, and a meane to make a now choiſe: which change, what good it ſhal yéeld,
<pb facs="tcp:16252:7"/> your ſelfe ſhall challenge, whoſe good reporte hath bound me to commence my deſerts, to receiue their cenſure by your doome. To boaſt what I am were frinelous, for that your fréends are alreadie priuie to my eſtate, and to ſay how well I loue you were booteles, for that women loue to trie ere they truſt, yet vnles I ſhould ſay more then I haue ſaide, I ſhould ſéeme to ſay nothing: though to ſay more then is ſpoken already were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éerely fooliſh For thus ſtands the caſe, I haue made choiſe of you for my ſecond wife, and haue already your fréends good will, there reſtes therefore nothing but a confirmation of your duetie, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeing to that they haue confirmed: thus conuning to a full point, he cloſed vp his period with a brace of ſmirking kiſſes, which wrought with his Louer, as a ſtrong pyll dooth with a ſore ſicke patient: namely, they forced her to anſwere him thus threwdely. The aſſurance of your good fortune Sir, hath made you highly beholden to her deitie, that dauncing in the morrice of good matches, you ſhould be led by her to ſo good hap: but belike it was ouer good to continue long, either her kindenes being ouermatched with your vnconſtancie, or your good happe ouer ruled by fortunes cruelty: They euer change and lightly neuer but for the worſe: which the rather ſéemes ſo vnto me, by the ſure knowledge I haue of your ſecond choice, that is ſo far vnequall to your reported firſt match, as I know your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king would not remain long, or my miſliking would come too too ſoone; becauſe I am not able to follow what you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt wife hath performed, and you will be vnwilling to beare with the wants your ſecond choice muſt be enriched with. But peraduenture I miſtake your meaning, for where as I thinke you ſue to haue me to your ſecond wife, you ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eke but to haue my good wil to liue with my fréende, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r my duetie (as you ſay) muſt not gainſay their pleaſure, nor will I for that matter, but with all my hart if you haue their licence for your boord, haue my good will to obtaine your bed there alſo, for their houſe is at their owne commaundement. Then doubt I not (replyed he) to
<pb facs="tcp:16252:8"/> haue you for my bedfellow. But that doubt I (anſwered ſhe) for that I know the contrary. Why dare you (quoth he) to diſobay your Fathers commaundement? No (ſayd ſhe) ſo it be for my commoditie. It ſhall be both for your profite and prefe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment. Make me to beléeue that (quoth ſhe) and then peraduenture it may be a bargaine. Why woman (ſaid he) I deſerue your better. Take her (anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe) and I will not be matched to your inferiour. Why then I ſée you do ſcant loue me? I vſe it not (quoth ſhe) and yet I ſweare I will mocke you, rather then mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with you. With which being highly diſpleaſed, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed thrée or foure crabbed tearmes, being liueries of his cholerick long toung, and ſo departed.</p>
            <p>A ſhame goe with him, thought <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> whatſoeuer ſhe thought, and with all ſuch Louers; louers? with a hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, lubbers I may better tearme them. What monſtrous matches are ſuch as are ſhuffled vp after the ſelfe ſame order? Suppoſe ſhe had beene fearefull and durſt not to haue reſiſted the receipt of what ſhe lothed, imagine ſhe had béene fooliſh and could not haue iudged of affection? thinke ſhe had béene forward, and would haue béene glad of any one? alas poore wretch, I pittie the ſuppoſition, what ſhould I haue ſaid to the confirmation? I know aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly ſhe ſhould haue ſighed whatſoeuer I had ſaide, and mourning ſhould haue béen her companion, what ere had béen my communication; he would haue daunſt with her portion, while ſhe had drooped through want of affection; he would haue loathed her company, for that ſhe was not a dayly commoditie; her life ſhould haue béen like the hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that are at euery mans commaundement for the hire, and her ioy as momentary as the floriſhing gréene graſſe in Iuly. Pitifully ſhould ſhe haue liued, puniſhed by him without pitie, and this is my reaſon of the poſſibilitie; for that it is moſt likely he loued her not, &amp; how well any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vſe them they loue not, let them ſpeake that ſuſpect not. Now that he loued her not, may be proued both by his kinde of wrong, careleſlye ſuing vnto her, peremptorily v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping
<pb facs="tcp:16252:8"/> her Fathers authoritie, which was a band to lye her to obedience, though a bad meane to obtaine her curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. For affection is not to be limitted, nor loue to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarily, hatred followes feare, and feare fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runnes miſlike, and how we loue thoſe we regarde not, iudge they that woo and obtaine not? But this cuſtome is too common and ouer cruell, namely, a wooing of fréends, and a conſtraint of loue, I would not ſay, compelling, but for feare it ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue been taken for compelling. Were <hi>Honeſtie</hi> a Iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, they ſhould either lye in the ſtockes a fortnight, or marry her I would match him with, which ſhould ſéeke a wife after this order. I thinke verily he would rather ſtay his ſtint by the héeles, then be bound to the other inconuenience; and yet he could finde in his hart to binde another to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bad bargaine. This is charitie, yea &amp; neuer a whit of honeſtie, being ſo farre from ciuilitie, as the Millers craft is from true dealing. Now truely tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to deale as we would be dealt with, is ſent to the hedge a begging, and neighbourly loue is made a hacknie, being ſo worne to the bones with ſéeking a good Maiſter, as his ſkinne will hang on the buſh ſhortely.</p>
            <p>I haue heard a reporte of a paſſing kinde man, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of his wife at a Seſſions, for piſſing a pot full, iudging thereby ſhe was diſhoneſt, and that ſame man ſhortly after burying his wiſe, ſued to a maide, after the manner aforeſaid: he had obtained her fréends good will, and were at a point for the Maidens loue, yet on a time ſhe was troubled with the head-ake, at his being with her, whereof he ſo miſliked, as in the morning he went to the Phiſitions to haue their opinions to what diſeaſe it coulde turne, and vpon their reporte left her. I am aſſured I haue erred in no point, vnleſſe I haue miſtooke the laſt, putting the Phiſitions opinion in the roome of his owne bad mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; it was no diſeaſe indéede that miſliked or miſled him, but it was of the Fathers purſſe, not of the Daughters head: well ſhe was well prouided for in miſſing of him, and if he ſped any thing the better, let him boaſt of it, but
<pb facs="tcp:16252:9"/> 
               <hi>Honeſtie</hi> can iudge no better of the remnant of his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, then his action giues the verdict of him, which is as bad as may be.</p>
            <p>But to another that hapned on one that had the too thanke, with whom he would not matry for feare the hollowneſſe of her tooth ſhould corrupt her bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, and ſo annoye his colde ſtomack. It was colde indéede, and I would ſuch ſtomacks might be heated with redde hotte gold, as chéer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as ſcalding leade. Well to a third, he liked her parents wel, for that they were honeſt &amp; godly, and as well of the maiden, becauſe ſhe ſéemed modeſt: to be bréef, he could find no ſaulte in either of them, onely his feare was that the Daughter would be ſomewhat ſhrewiſh, for that ſhe had a long noſe, and thereupon gaue her ouer. If her noſe had béene long enough, I think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he might haue ſmelt a knaue, but I am aſſured ſhe knew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a churle, and ſo let her claime him whereſoeuer ſhe ſées him. Yet one more of the ſame ſtampe, and ſo we will leaue them. This was a wooer in graine, who had gone ſo far, as they were at next doore to he aſkt in the Church. The wedding apparel was bought, the day appointed, yea and I may tel you, many of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> geſſe bid, only there was no aſſurance, for that he abhorred: but it fortuned that before the day there dyed a rich man that left a welthie widdow, to whom he made ſo ſecret loue, as he wonne her good will within a fortnight after the death of his predeceſſour: well, notwithſtanding to ſaue his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit credit, and preſerue his hypocriticall honeſtie, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted dayly to his olde ſwéete hart, with whom vpon ſome ſmal reaſon he fel at ods, vſing her ſo vnkindly in ſpéeches, as he drew teares for ſorrow. Glad of this, though tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his earneſt into ieſt, he called her vnto him, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of many of her Fathers ſeruants, then ſwearing that if the tooke him not about the necke &amp; kiſſed him, he would neuer marry with her as long as he liued. Which y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yong Gentlewoman refuſed to doe, partely for that he had iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her highly, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rather leaſt ſuch fondnes ſhould ſéeme immodeſtie to the ſeruants: vpon whoſe denial, in a great
<pb facs="tcp:16252:9"/> fume he ſlung forth of the doores, and in a rage as if of ſpight, within one fortnight after he matcht with the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe aforeſaid. But to tell you what a life ſhe lead with him, were to hunt from the purpoſe, yet aſſure your ſelfe it was ſo bad, as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> world iudged this maid neuer better bleſt then in not being beſtowed ne caſt away vpon him.</p>
            <p>Such and of the ſame ſorte are theſe money-woers, that ſue firſt to the Father to ſaue labour, for ſpéede they will, and if they miſſe in one place, they knowe another where they will practiſe. And how can it be iudged other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſéeing their meaning in vſing that meane importes no leſſe: for thinke they, if I haue the Fathers good will, the daughter will be eaſilie wonne, and if I miſſe of his, I ſaue that time and labour, in ſuing to the maide, beſides the giftes I ſhould beſtowe. Ha ha, I haue him by ſent, and what thinke you of him? in faith no otherwiſe then <hi>Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> beléeues. You ſmell a Foxe, I and a ranke one too, whoſe breach is ſo ſtainde with this gilding matter, as it may eaſely bée iudged what muck hée loues. Alas good hearts, that are coupled with ſuch bad mindes, this is loue? true, but what loue? couetous loue, hatefull diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hipocriticall affection, and what not that is contrarie to the ſwéete ſoueraigne loue, which ſues for kiſſes and not for co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, which craues the heart &amp; nothing e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe; for with it al ſhe hath is his, and he that wil looke for more, I would he had a halter, and he ſhall not want it in hell, howſoeuer he ſpéedes here. Fie fie, mariages for the moſt part are at this day ſo made, as looke how the butcher bies his cattel, ſo wil men ſel their children. He that bids moſt ſhal ſpéed ſooneſt, &amp; ſo he hath money, we care not a fart for his honeſtie. Well it hath not béen ſo, and I hope it wil not be long ſo, &amp; I wil aſſure you, loues common-wealth wil neuer floriſh vntil it be otherwiſe. Why, it is a common practize to aſke the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what hée will giue with his childe, and what is that differing from cheapening an Ore? And it is as common, that if ſhe be fat, it is a bargaine, but if leane, ſhe muſt ſtay another cuſtomer. Out alas what loue is this, in faith if I
<pb facs="tcp:16252:10"/> might haue ſped better in another place, come to notice after I haue bought your daughter, ſhe ſhall pay for it, or I will make dice on her bones. Apittifull partenerſhip, where there is no greater loue, and how can but one of them be vndone? He will vſe her ill, becauſe he loues her not, and ſhée cannot loue him for not vſing her well; for whome we feare we hate, and what then? Hée will prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe her ende, ſhe will wiſh his death, and while they liue together, it will be ſo full of heart breakings through quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and contentions, as woe to them both, I and to the third too, that was ſo forward to make ſo bad a matche. But howſoeuer they two ſpéede, I am aſſured ſhée will ſpéede worſe, as for hir huſband, he will not want ercuſes to defend his knauerie, and hir Father muſt beléeue him, becauſe of hir former credit giuen vnto him; ſo that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented ſhe muſt be, how diſcontented ſo euer ſhe liues, and beare it ſhe muſt, vntill her hart breake, which happie day muſt ende her miſerie, and ſet my craftie wooer at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</p>
            <p>Thus much for my ſecond corner, and now to my third couple, which were ciuilly ſeated on a benche together, they being the one a batcheler, and the other a widdowe, which was wooed by him after this like order. It were fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie forſéeth (quoth he) to vſe circumſtances, ſince you are ſo well acquainted with the like practize: but to leaue them and come to the matter, which is (as I thinke) the beſt meane to pleaſe vs both, you ſhall vnderſtand that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the good reporte your honeſt life hath deſerued, I haue conceiued ſo good liking of you, as I ſhould thinke my ſelfe happie, if I ſhould ſpéede no worſſe. I thanke you (anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe) for your good will: but ſurely Sir, I thinke you haue deceiued your ſelfe. For peraduenture you imagine, or it hath béen vntruely reported, that I am the woman, which indéede I am not, namely ritche, for that my decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed huſband made ſome ſhowe to the world, but if that bée your thought, I aſſure you, you are deceiued. You miſtake my meaning (replied hée) for it is no ſuch matter; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:16252:10"/> not ſo much your wealth, as I doo your matronlike modeſtie, my ſelfe is young, and I haue a trade, and am, I thanke God, of my ſelfe able to maintaine a woman. But I doo rather deſire to match with your like then with a younger, for that you knowe better, both what belongs to a man, as alſo to vſe thriftely what I get. And moreouer my ſelfe is not ſo young, but that I am meeter to match with a widd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we then to marrie with a maide, and would be moſt glad, if it might be my good happe to ſpeede with you. I cannot tell (quoth ſhe) what your good ſpeede may be; I knowe you not, and therefore I hope you will giue me leaue to enquire of you, which done I will ſend you your anſwere by ſuch a day, in the meane time I wiſh you well.</p>
            <p>I mary, <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> &amp; what then? no marry theſe, forth ſhe went to her broker to will him to ſearch after his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, vſing that manner which vſurers can beſt diſcloſe, which is their practiſe in putting forth their money. This was a paſſing commoditie, for what better then a ritche widdowe? but that fooliſh enquirie ſpoyled all: had ſhee thankt him heartily, deſired farther libertie, and had made ſearch into his eſtate ſecretly, ſhee had ſhewed her ſelfe the wiſer: but ſo bluntly to ſaie, giue mee leaue to enquire of you, ſhewed as bad bringing vp, as might bee poſſible. But tut, I like her the better, becauſe ſhe could not diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for ſhe alas did but followe the common trade, dooing with the ape, but what ſhe had ſeene done before her. She had heard her huſband inſtruct his prentices to make a profit, and ſhe thought ſhe might trie the ſame for her own good. I would ſhee and others knewe what was good for them, they would then rather reſpect the man then money. But this couetouſnes ſpoyles all, though I would I had more, is too much in our mouthes, for followed ſhe not the greedie deſire of adding muck to much? might ſhee not as well haue liued with this man, that had a trade as good, yea much better then her huſbands was, as ſhee did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with him? Shee had no children, ſuppoſe ſhe had, they
<pb facs="tcp:16252:11"/> were prouided for well, and what greater charge woulde this haue brought? he had a care to liue, or elſe hee would haue ſought to loue without reſpect; for who knowes not that ſhe is as able to ſatiſfie a mans deſire, that hath little, as ſhe that hath much, if we onely regarde pleaſure? Take this on <hi>Hone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies</hi> credit, that hee that buildes his loue on ſuch reaſon, as hauing little, hée will choſe one that hath ſomewhat, wil proue a better match vnto thée, then him that brings mountaines. Beware when lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with maintenance, if the heart remembers, I am thus much beholden vnto her, ſhée loued mée or elſe ſhée would neuer haue matcht with me, ſhe made me a man, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worſe then nothing, how much better might ſhe haue done, if ſhe had not béen led with affection, and ſuch like: It will alſo remember the duetie this kindnes requireth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen like for like, leaſt the worſe crie ſhanie of him. How happie ſhould parents be, were this in their rememb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce at their mariges making? how bleſſed ſhould their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be, if the like practiſes were vſed? and what a flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing commonwealth would that be, where equalitie of birth (which alwaies ſhould bée regarded ſpecially on the mans ſide) ſhould bée linked to abundance, whereby the number of gentle beggers ſhould be decreaſed, and the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouernement of wealth will be auoided. One man ſhould not haue his cofersful, and twentie want it that better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it. How many able men ſhould we haue (if this were vſed) to ſerue and ſet forth men for the princes ſeruice? where now I am but one man, and I am bound but to my ſtint, to finde one mans charge, though I haue fiue mens liuings. But no more, this is too ſerious for <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> &amp; I meruaile how I fell into this vaine, ſince I ſtudied to bee pleaſant. What, thinke you, did my widdowe after her ſearch of enquirie, for you muſt thinke that the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tcheler longed for his anſwere? Marry though ſhe was not a fore in her ſpéeches, yet ſhée proued no leſſe in her dooing, for now ſhée kept her houſe as cloſely as hée dooth his holde craftely. She miſlikt of the man, for what cauſe geſſe you,
<pb facs="tcp:16252:11"/> if you knew as much as I knowe, you would ſweare, not for lack of honeſtie, or becauſe he was vnthriſtie. But wil you knowe whie? he had not the hundreds lying by him, as the reporte went ſhée had left her, and therefore ſhée thought it néedeles any one ſhould loſe ſo much labour, as to fulfill her promiſe in carrying his anſwere. Yet if that were all, it were well, I and it had béen well for him (for the ſauing of ſhoo lether) if ſhe would haue ſpoken with him at his comming to fetche it: But my widdowe would not be within, or elſe ſhe was buſie: and thus was his kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes requited. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of the diuell, is this a méete reward for affection, nay ſuppoſe it be no more, the good will was it well requited? Me thinkes that if his dog had come, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e deſerued better entertainement then to haue béen beaten away, and ſhee had dealt better if ſhée had ſent himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a crabbed anſwere, then ſo vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to vſe him by ſléeueles ercuſes. And well it were if ſhee had no more fellowes, but out vpon them, there are too many ſuch, whoſe coye nicenes e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>preſſe their miſchieuous fondenes, for ſpeake they will with any man that come, vnles a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald fore runnes the ſewtor.</p>
            <p>In my opinion, and it ſhall bée grounded vpon reaſon, ſuch widdowes are worthie to ſit while their bréeches growe to their ſeates, as refuſe to anſwer all conuners of what degrée ſoeuer, and becauſe I promiſt you reaſon, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be it. Who knowes not that whoſoeuer ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for the like match, winneth a thouſand incombrances with his good ſpéede, for he that knowes not that care ſhal be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with his beſt contentment, ſhall fall into a pitte before he beware of it. And who, were it not for his ſoules health, would imbrace ſuch an inconuenience for a little commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie? I and the beſt mariage, is but a little commoditie, in reſpect of the continuall carking that comes with it. If then, as who ſaies it is otherwiſe, a man makes ſo great ſuite for ſo ſmall hearts eaſe (reſpecting the earthly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) deſerues not he a good countenance, or at leaſt a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come that longs for ſo bad a bargaine? In my iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:16252:12"/> and it ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umpe with mine opinion, that woman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> much more beholden to the man that would match with her, then to her parents that haue brought her vp; for they did what ere they did, of duety, &amp; this doth what might be vndone of mere deuotion. Why, thinke the beſt you can, thinke for your ſelues, ſuppoſe one that hath nothing comes to craue your loue, did he only reſpect your wealth without his owne welfare (and hée that thinkes to haue welfare without dealing wel with you, he reckens with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his hoſteſſe, and ſhal finde a new bil of charges) had he not much better to hazſurd the taking of a purſe by the high way? Yes doubtles, for were hée by that means brought vnto miſerie, he might haue death at his cal, to rid him from extremitie: but now being grieued vnceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he may ſéeke for death, but méete with the diuell, hope for an ende, but féele the want of it continually. Yet come we to one further point, imagine ſome men that bée ouer-unruly, deſire to haue acceſſe into your companie, if you knowe them for ſuch companions, I would holde you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to admit them into your preſence, but ſhall your hart but ſay, I ſuſpect without trial, you cannot out-runne the crime of want of deſcretion. It is beſt therefore, you that feare ſuch reſorte, to harbour your ſelues, during the time of the heate of the market in ſuch places, as the countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your protectors ſhall preuent ſuſpect, and diſparage the practiſe of ſuch vndecent behauiour; or otherwiſe to appropriate vnto your houſes ſuch helpes as ſhall bée likely to foreſtall the like miſchiefe. That euery one may bee anſwered is <hi>Hone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies</hi> meaning, for vnles they bee, they haue not their due, nor doo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou ſhewe your ſelues to de inriched with that cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſie, which wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dowes deſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dooth challenge. For let me tell you, and enſure as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as knowe it not, that a man ſhall finde more pleaſure in lying in the campe, being dayly threatned with the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of his enemie, then in lodging with a wiſe, vnles his wiſdome be the greater. And I knowe you looke for my reaſon, then for this cauſe, for that their vnconſtancie
<pb facs="tcp:16252:12"/> bréedes more feare then the ſhot brings hurt, and their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heart will craue more gouernement to content them, then the other will aſke forecaſt to preuent the danger they bring with them. For a ſtéele coate reſiſtes the harme of a muſket, but what garment ſhall out ſtand her threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the horne? That man amongſt Souldiers is counted accurſt, that is ſtrucken with a great ſhot, and that huſband thriſe bleſt among married men, that is not continually wounded with ſome miſdemeanor, or other, he ſhall eſpie in his wife? well, I ſay no more, becauſe I am a batcheler: but <hi>Honeſtie</hi> muſt ſpeake the trueth, or ſhame will follow him.</p>
            <p>It is wiſdome to looke before lepping, but extreame fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to ſtand vpon nothing: hée or ſhée that makes many doubtes, ſhall neuer want care, and ſhe wil il rule a charge that cannot charme a knaue. Speake the diuell faire and he will be ſatiſfied, and what woman knowes not how to flatter? It is good to knowe vice, that we may ſhun that euill, and as good to trie the honeſtie of wooers, that you may not ſpéede the worſe. You ſhall often finde a kings heart clad in a thred-bare coate, and a ſenators wiſdome harbored in a youthfull head: vertue goes not by birth, nor deſcretion by yeares, for there are olde fooles, and young councellers, counterfeit knaues &amp; crabbed churles, the one being clad in a lambes ſkinne, and the other kept warme with Foxe furre. Nature makes, but fortune clothes, a ritch knaue therefore may march in the habit of a true meaning gentleman, when poore <hi>Honeſtie</hi> muſt goe as he is able, bee it in a mouldie caſſock. I haue heard it credibly reported, that there was a ritch widdowe fell here in England, which had left her liuing enough to maintaine a younger brother, and vnto her did reſorte ſuch an one, as had not ſildome flung out at a bootie, nor would haue cared much if it had béen his father, ſo he had met him in a conuenient place. This young gentleman (yet not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oung, for he was about fortie) came vnto this wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, to craue her good wil, vſing as ſpéedie tearmes as he
<pb facs="tcp:16252:13"/> deſired quicke ſpéede. Hée tolde her his name, ſo well knowne throughout the countrie fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſhifting liuer, as he ſpake no ſooner then hee was well knowne vnto hir. Whome ſhe vſed courteouſly, anſwering him after this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I hope gentle ſir (quoth ſhe) you will giue me leaue to anſwer you as ſpéedely as you bluntly aſke the queſtion: And with all my heart (replied hée,) for that is my deſire. Then aſſure you thus much (ſaid ſhe) that if there were no more men in the world beſides your ſelfe, I would not marrie with you. A ſhort and ſower anſwere (quoth he) yet let mée aſſure you, that onely ſuch an one (naming himſelfe) will haue you, and ſo tooke his leaue, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in as good order, as ſhée had in kinde manner v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him. Shortly after at a méeting with many of his companions, he craued their aide, finding them as forward to performe any thing hée ſhould require, as hée would wiſh. Vnto whome hée ſhewed his whole intention, the rather deſiring their helpes, for that they had béen part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with him in as great hazards, well agréed vppon the match, they rode towards the widdowes houſe, comming thither in the euening about ſupper-time, when it was very darke, whereby their companie coulde not bée deſcried. They knockte at the gate, and was anſwered by the porter, that being aſked who was within, certified them according to his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Him they ſo hampered, as gagde hée was and bound, being laide forth of the way, which done, they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed further, entring the hall with their drawne ſwordes, where they found all the ſeruants at Supper. They had no weapons néere them but bones, being vnméete inſtrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to reſiſt armed men; and dogges they were not to be wonne by ſuch baites. Therefore eaſily one by one they were bound and laide on a heape, the wooer in the meane time with two of his mates, being in the Parlor with the widdowe that was garded with two ſutors, being Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of account in that Country; he vnmaſked him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe, for they had al viſards, and tolde the widdow he was
<pb facs="tcp:16252:13"/> come for her: at what time one of them grewe cholerick, and I thinke it was he that was likeſt to haue ſped beſt, for he was placed on the benche néereſt to her hart, and drew his poyniard, the beſt weapon he had at that inſtant, making as if he meant to darte the ſame; but vpon better conſideration had, be put vp his Dagger, and was conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be hound with his fellowe. All of them being bound they got y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Widowe foorth, and bound her with a towel behinde one of them, hauing before their departure hid all the Saddles and turned forth the Horſes out from y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> houſe. Ouer a long plaine they rode ſo through a wood, where being out of greateſt danger, he himſelfe the wooer got vp before the widdowe, entreating her to conſider of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, not ſo much he himſelfe reſpecting his own weale, as he regarded his fréends welfare, whome he had drawen into that deſperate action. But it was all in vaine, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gré<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe would not, ſhe ſware rather to dye then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which ſéemed little to remedie his affection. Wel, in ſhort time they were come to a place prepared for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> nonce, where they found a good fire with a Parſon, and other good company, aſſembled together about the ſame matter. It was a wonderfull rainie euening, ſo that all of them were throughly wet, but there ſhe wanted nothing ſhe could deſire, nor ſpared he kinde words to winne her good will, which was ſo long in graunting, as before the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, Hue and cry was followed into that Towne. Whereof he hauing notice, came to her with his laſt hope, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lling her, that as ſhe was a woman, either then or neuer to conſent to the ſauing of all their liues. When ſhe ſéeing no remedy, but either ſhe muſt relent or they repent it: will you (quoth ſhe) be good to my boy <hi>Tom?</hi> for ſhe had one onely childe called <hi>Thomas.</hi> To ſay I would (replyed he) in this extremitie, might be ſaide to be but flatterie, but aſſure thy ſelfe I will, and much better then I will boaſt on: vpon which agréement, they were foorthwith maried. Soone after he called her aſide, and tolde her ſhe was now his wife, whoſe credit was her good regarde, we
<pb facs="tcp:16252:14"/> ſhal, I know (quoth he) be brought for this before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, at which time vnleſſe you vſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> matter thus cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye as to affirme this was your owne practiſe, to ſhewe your loue, and ſhun a bad reporte, we ſhall notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſmart for it. Which ſhe promiſed to doo, and did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede no leſſe, all them being ſhortly after apprehended and brought vp to anſwere it at the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell Table, where ſhe tolde ſo good a tale for him and his fellowes to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect aforeſaide, as the faulte was remitted and they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged. Now that you may vnderſtand how well he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited this her kindnes, ſhe liued with him a long time, and yet leſſe then a doſen yéeres, and dying left this good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of his vſage towards her: namely, that neuer wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man liued with a more kinde man then ſhe had found him, with other ſuch probable tokens of the certainty thereof, as a Countrie can witnes the ſame. Him ſelfe liued not long after her, at his death leauing her ſonne <hi>Thomas</hi> fiue hundred pounds by the yéere, ouer and aboue his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers liuing, which he himſelfe had purchaſed by his good huſbandrie.</p>
            <p>What ſay you to this vnthrifte? was not ſhe put to a ſhrewde triall? ſhe was and it proued paſſing wel. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then ſhould yonger brothers be reiected, or why they that haue little be vnregarded? ſurely becauſe the hart is couetous and miſtruſtfull, and womens mindes are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring being neuer contented. They ſo much thirſte after preferment, as often they ouer-leape amendement, and iumpe iuſt into a worſer predicament.</p>
            <p>Many looke ſo long for aboundance of mucke, as as they fall into a quagmire of miſeries, hauing ſiluer to looke on, though wanting mony to ſupply many wants, hauing a faire ſhewe and a ſhrewde kéeper, one that hath more then enough, &amp; yet will not part with any thing: <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> knowes many of theſe, and they féele more then I can tell you. Who goes for the moſt parte worſe ſhod then the Shoomakers childe, and who hath leſſe mone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in her purſſe then ſhe whoſe Huſband hath moſt in his cheſt?
<pb facs="tcp:16252:14"/> But for that I am ſome what ſtraied out of my way, I will return to my firſt widdowe before my ſhooes be quite worne: My forenamed Bacheler that neither by himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or his fréends, could ſpeake with her to know her anſwer, deuiſed this concluſion, to ſend her a Letter by a fréend, not ſo much for the matter there in ſet downe, as that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> might be a meane to entice her to be ſpoken with, which indéed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proued to ſome purpoſe. For to the Meſſenger ſhe came, and after notice giuen from whome the Letter was ſent, gods Lord (quoth ſhe) did not my fréend giue him his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere? No, replyed the Meſſenger, for he craues no more by this Letter. Surely (quoth ſhe) I thanke him for his good will, but I am not minded that way. What way (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed he) not to marry? Yes ſaide ſhe, but not with one ſo yong. Now you ſhall vnderſtand her ſimple excuſe, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made, for in a mans iudgement it would not be thought there was much difference betwéene their ages. And as it was gathered after, ſhe meant one way, and the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger tooke it an other, for ſhe meant yong in ſubſtance, though he vnderſtood it for yéers: as after further talk ſhe plainely expreſſed. What ſhall <hi>Honeſtie</hi> ſay more of her? in ſooth nothing but to pray either for the amendement of her and her companions, or elſe that this puniſhment may be inflicted vpon them: that is to ſay, that they may be ſo haunted vntill they deale better, as they may not péepe foorth of their houſes, without as much wondermen as the Owle hath that flieth in the day time. And doo they deſerue leſſe, that make fooles? it hath béene a fuſtie ſaying, <hi>Qui moccat moccabitur,</hi> and vntill that proue true by practice, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> falles out true often vnlookte for, we that are to ſpéed ſhall neuer finde better. If all men will agrée to <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> we wil keepe a Cronicle of ſuch wenches, my ſelfe will be ſpeak the regiſtreſhip, and though it be no great office, yet it may doo much good. But now to a fourth kinde.</p>
            <p>Which were a thriſe-made, not a thréed-bare Widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and a fiue times left Widdowe, both of them being ſo much in Fortunes bookes, as they were endowed with the
<pb facs="tcp:16252:15"/> thouſands. They ſoone agréed vpon the matter, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſhorte time were married, vnto whoſe houſe hauing heard them boaſt of their ſubſtance, I often reſorted to ſée what good chéere they kept, I was twiſe there together in Chriſtmas time, but neuer could ſée hotte meate, yet good ſtore of cold by reaſon they had had foure daies before many gueſts. But ſince the holly dayes hoping for hetter fare, I found him and ſhe ſet at a couple of red. Herring, &amp; a ſlice of barrel butter, colde fare as I thought for a tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day ſupper. Alas how were the ſeruants dieted, when they had no better? I would haue thought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faulte to haue béene in her, vntill ſhe ſaide vnto me, that ſhe was ſorrye ſhe had no better fare for <hi>Honeſtie;</hi> when the olde Churle replied, holde thée content wife, he is welcome, I thanke God I haue this for him. I thanke your worſhip ſaide I, though I thought, I beſhrewe the Churles hart. But there of force muſt I lodge too, for that I had ouer farre home, and he that had fedde me ſo hungerly, had found talke enough to kéepe me with him till midnight. I muſt confeſſe I lay better then I had ſupped, lodgde in the next Chamber to themſelues, there being nothing but a thinne wall betwéene vs. After my firſt ſléepe I heard them two very lowde, and though I did not greatly deſire to be a partaker of their ſecret, yet I could not chooſe vnles I had béene either naturally or artificially deafe. They were at ſo hotte words, as he cryed, out vpon thée old beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly whore, with other moſt ſhamefull tearmes, ſhe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by being forced thus to complaine. Alas that euer I was borne to ſée your face, I was no begger when I met with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou, for I brought with me as good as twentie thouſand pounds, which now being at your diſpoſition, you deale thus crabbedly with me, méeting together in reſpect but yeſterday: what hope reſteth to me of the end, ſeeing the beginning is ſo bad? you diet me with hardmeat, and chéer me with crabbed vſage, I can neither haue a penny in my purſſe, nor a good ſhooe to my foote. I gréeue to heare my ſeruants repine thereat, though I cannot amend it, and
<pb facs="tcp:16252:15"/> for that I tell you of it which may redreſſe it, thus you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile me. Holde thy peace olde whore (quoth he) or I will make thée, if they like it not, let them mend theirſelues, and either charme your toung or I will clapperclaw your bones: with which cooling carde, ſhe was glad to be qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, as I geſſe, for I could beare no more of her at that time.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Honeſtie</hi> hauing leaſure to thinke of what he had heard, ſtill harpt of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> twentie thouſand pounds, which as I thought, was méeter to haue made a King, then to haue pleaſed a churle, with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I condemned his cruelty, and piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her chaunce, ſo long thinking on her hard fortune, as I fell a ſléepe, taking vp the remnant of my mornings nap. Well, before I roſe my olde carle was vp, and before I was ready gone ahroad, when ſuddenly comming foorth of my lodging, forced to paſſe through his Chamber, I found the good olde woman ſhedding teares ſo aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as I could not but gréeue for company. But ſéeing me, ſhe rowzed vp her ſelfe and would haue ſhadowed her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, yet at laſt aſſured I had heard the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arre, ſhe ſaide ſhe was ſorrie I had béene diſquieted, the which I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, ſaying, I was more greeued for her then for my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting, for had that béene the worſt, <hi>Honeſtie</hi> hath béene farre woorſe troubled. Ah good ſir (quoth ſhe) this is their fortune that are couetous, for I had enough left me to haue liued like a woman, if I could haue béen ſo contented: but aiming at dignitie hath béen my deſtruction, and longing after promotion hath brought me to this miſerie: my laſt Huſband was accounted a good houſholder, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to the beſt in the pariſh, but he being gone, and my hope to become a Lady, hath ledde me to this ill bargaine. Ah gentle <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> I was no meane woman when I met with him, but he thinkes, for that I haue turned my Cloth to ſilke, he hath made me happie. How happie had I béene, if I had neuer ſéene him, but too late it is to wiſh, and folly to complaine, for that it was my owne choice that hath matcht my ſelfe with ſuch a churle. He clothes me in gay
<pb facs="tcp:16252:16"/> coates for his owne credit, but with them cloyes me with multitudes of diſcontentments: abroad he is gone, and perchaunce I ſhall not ſée him till bed time, nor are ſuch trickes plaide ſeldome, when he leaues nothing, what néed ſoeuer we ſhould haue of any thing, but what the houſhold prouiſion is, the beſt being no better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your yeſternights fare. If he brings any bodie home with him, we muſt run to the Cookes to ſaue fiering, nor can a bit of bread be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten without an account giuen to him, he ſcarcheth euery corner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chides for euery candles end he findes miſplaced, and if perchaunce he happe on a cruſt, he will make as much ſtirre as if it were the loſſe of a Cow: he will prie into the greace pot, and hunt after the Tappe droppings, to be bréefe, the creame pot ſhould be ouerlooked by him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day once at the leaſt, and his fiering ſurueied as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, a Chéefe cannot be cut without his leaue, nor a ſticke be burned without grutching. Nor doo I ſo much gréeue at this in reſpect of my ſelfe, as for that my ſeruants want their due, their want being more irkeſome vnto me, then this ſcant: for what will they let to reporte, and who can blame them? or who will ſtaye in ſuch an houſe, and not without reaſon? ſo that dayly diſcredit is heaped on vs and continuall care for looking after new ſeruants neuer from vs. This is my greateſt hart breake, and my ſute to haue this redreſſed is our only breake-peace. He ſumes when I informe him of what I haue heard, and ſtampes when I tell him it is not well, nor wil I tel thée all, for that this is too much, nor ſhouldſt thou haue knowne of thus much for me, except his crabbednes had made the path. But hark he is come in, for the paſſion of God hide thy ſelfe, for if he ſhould know thou wert not gon, he will miſtruſt vs, and ſmart I ſhall for vs both.</p>
            <p>Now the Diuell breake his necke, or God amend him, thoght I, yet for feare of her harm I was conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be lockt vp by her into a cloſet, where I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraind to ſtay while y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> téeth chattered in my head, before we could be rid of him. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, at laſt by good fortune a companion of his fetcht him
<pb facs="tcp:16252:16"/> forth to dinner, who being gone, I was let forth, an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary fier being made for my welcome down; &amp; to make me a mends, ſhe had ſent a bracelet ſhe had, of which he knew not, to paune, prouiding ſo good fare for my Dinner, as I was not at better all the Chriſtmas. But while we were eating of it, our mirth could not be much, her feare was ſo great of his comming home, but we making as quick ſpéede as our téeth would let vs, after we had doone I thanked her, taking my leaue and departing. Wel, my backe was ſcarce turnde, when ſhe bid her men and maids to beſtirre them that the kitchen might be dreſt vp and the remnant of our Chriſtmas fire to be quencht and caſt into the priuie, leaſt his ſearch ſhould finde out the brandes, and that bréede no little diſquietnes to them all. Alas poore wretch thought I, how many ſeruants are there which liue at more eaſe and ſtand in leſſe awe then thou dooſt? Is this a wiues protion? doubtles no, but a iuſt plague for couetouſnes, for they which cannot vſe a benefite when they haue it to a good purpoſe, ſhall want it when they would, and ſeeke it when they cannot finde it. Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall not eſcape hell, for how farre I pray you was ſhe from it? her good daies died with her matching with him, and if there be any purgatory betwéene vs and hell, ſhe was in it, and thereby at the next doore to that dungeon. I would but all couetous mindes were plagued but with a dramme of the like diſcontent, I would haue theirs but a ſeauen-nights puniſhment, whereas ſhe muſt endure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture ſeauen yéeres torment. <hi>Honeſtie</hi> thinkes ſuch a meſſe of miſerie would bring them to a banquet of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes at their deliuerie from that wretchednes. If many of our coye dames that cannot be content with any thing, and are ſo curious, as daily dainties ſéeme nothing vnto them, were but pincht a while with her morſelles, I am perſwaded it would ſaue their huſbands a great deale of charges in their diet thence after, and would make their ſeruants much happier, by being fréed from much néedeles labour. Their houſes would be pulled downe, and the
<pb facs="tcp:16252:17"/> delight of their curious poked ruffes would be ſet aſide, they would not reſpect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperfluous diſhes they vſe, nor regarde their ſuperſtitious curioſitie in rubbing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>owres of their houſes: what ſhould I ſay more? they would vſe obedience towards their Huſbands more, and brawling with their ſeruants leſſe, they would thinke of their owne happie liues &amp; pittie others; they would ſéeke to pleaſe, and be more eaſily pleaſed; they would liue contentedly, and be thankfull for ſo great proſperitie.</p>
            <p>The fiſhe that hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne ſtricken with the hook, feares the baite; the childe that hath burnte his fingers, dreades the candle; the horſe that hath beene puniſhed with the ſpurre, ſuſpects the wagging of the héele, and the apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theefe, begins to thinke on the halter. What delight brings ſweete things vnto them that neuer taſted of ſharp ſauce? or what an indifferent opinion carrie they of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, that haue neuer béene in miſerie? The vnridden Colte bites the ſnaffle while the olde horſe is glad to play with the bit, and they that are vſed to ſhackles, weare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without much annoiance: for that it is vſe that gets experience, and experience that brings profit. When a curſt Cow hath ſhort hornes, harme is leſſe ſuſpected, and if a crabbed cur be muſled there can be no danger. There are both baites to entice, and bobbes to make to forbeare: allurements to winne, and corrections to driue away; and he that thought this to be néedefull, knowes beſt to vſe it, which happens alwaies to vnbrideled nouices: once good ſpéede egges vs to a ſecond aduenture, and if twiſe a théefe hath eſcaped the halter, he will neuer leaue vntill he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe tiborne. My laſt Huſband was ſo good, makes ſome ſo deſirous of a ſecond, as their haſtie bargaine bringes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer late repentance. Like will to like, quoth the Diuell to the Collier, and ſome will neuer be ſatiſfied vntill their mouthes be filled with Clay. He that hath enough ſéekes for more, and ſo I carrie a great countenance I care not how I am beloued. Indéede what cannot money doo that will buye any thing, and yet honeſtie will purchaſe that
<pb facs="tcp:16252:17"/> which all the muck in the world cannot compaſſe, namely a good report for euer. Who knowes not that the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons man cannot line quietly, and why wil we not knowe that the aſpiring minde ſhall be brought lowe? The loue of your wealth is in your owne hands, but the key of your wittes kept by a higher guide. You may choſe a ritch man and hunt after an honeſt (yet ritches and honeſtie goe ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome together) but to ſay it ſhall be for your weale muſt craue anothers leaue. Hée that giues all things can giue thée both, and if thou wilt taſte of his liberalitie, built on his charitie, ſuſpect not and ſpeede well, feare and ſpeede ill, let therefore all thy care be built on his kindenes, and thou wilt be better contented with a kinde begger then a crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed churle. To take heede by another mans ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me is a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing warning, but if thou wilt needes try, take the hazard. When our neighbours houſe is on ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, we haue neede to beſtirre vs, and he that ſits ſtill at ſuch an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tremetie, is worthie to taſte of the like miſerie. To looke ere we lep is good counſell, yet to looke hartely and lep faintly, makes many to fall into a ditch dangerouſly, well a word to a wiſe man is enough, and there are few women but haue ſtore of wit, if they adde diſcretion vnto it. <hi>Honeſtie</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſhes them to vſe it ſo well as they neuer ſpeede ill.</p>
            <p>A ſift forte now followeth, which was a couple ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the midſt of the company, both of them being of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall yeares. He was a young ciuill gentleman, no leſſe proper then hée ſéemed wiſe, his diſcreet gouernement beautifying both; but ſhe, though ſhée had wit al will and was very proper, yet lacked ſhée the other ſtep to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, namely diſcreetenes in her behauior. Her immodeſt fondnes gaue ſuſpect of vnciuill lightnes, ſo that her ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forwardnes ſéemed to ouerlay her louers affection. Shée would hang about his neck before all that company, as a iacke of Napes doth ſitting on the bear heards ſhoulder, and kiſſe as openly as a dog ſcombers careleſly. She fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him at héeles like a tantinie pigge, and hong about him as if pinned to his ſlieue. He could not ſtirre without
<pb facs="tcp:16252:18"/> her company, nor ſcarce goe to make water, but ſhe would awaite on him. Thus much did ſhe not let to doe openly, and therefore I had the more deſire to ſée how ſhe ſpent her time ſecretly: which was as contrarie as might bée, for whereas ſhe would bee mad merrie in his company, in his abſence ſhe would be as mad melancholie. Shée then would ſit in a corner, as a dogge doth that is crept into a hole, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uing done a ſhroude turne, wetting her couch with teares for the lack of her ſwéet heart, as a childe doth the bed for want of a chamber-pot. But being in a good vaine, ſhée would pen paſſionate ſonnets, and in that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor did I once take her when ſhe had newly finiſhed this amorous dittie.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>SAd is the time while my deare loue is abſent:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eiſe waile my miſſe and tongue bewailes him wanting:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heart bleedeth teares that doo encreaſe my torment,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And yeelds forth ſighes which ſet it ſelfe a panting,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>While he is abſent, ſuch is my delight</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As is the ſaylers in a ſtormie night.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>If I chaunce ſing, with ſighes my ſongs be graced,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And in my tunes my grones my baces be:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grieuous complaints are for the trebles placed:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The meanes be teares, the tennor miſerie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Foure partes I beare and want the fifte alone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which is my ioye that with my loue is gone.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>When I ſhould ſpeake, my tongue forgets it talking:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When I ſhould write, my fingers are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nommed:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When I ſhould goe, my feete haue loſt their walking,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And euery part is dead of ſence bereaued.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor can I tell what is the cauſe of this,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Excep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> becauſe my heart with him gon is.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus dayes are nights to me while he is wanting,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And merieſt ſongs are plaintes for ioy departed:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16252:18"/>
               <l> 
                  <hi>My mirth is mone, my ſorrowe ſuccor wanting,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſences gon my bodie haue vnharted.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So that I liue aliue as being dead,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And by his abſence ſole, this death is bread.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>After the ſelfeſame order ſpends ſhée her well ſpent time, yéelding ſuch bitter ſighes, while ſhe is ſetting down the like paſſions as a horſe doth hartie neeſes, that is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with an extreame colde. Then pauſing a while on that ſhe hath done, weighing the eſtate of her lamentable caſe, ſhee caſtes her ſelfe vpon hir bed, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing againſt the fates the rancor of her heart after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anner. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and cruell ſiſters, that haue prol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my dayes to endure this miſerie; is this the force of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>crée, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my ioy by increaſing my d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes? Haue you drawne to this length the thread of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> life, now to cut the ſame with ſo ſharpe an edge-to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le? Cruell and vnkinde are ye ſo crabbedly to deale with a poore virgin, ſuffering me to liue to endure this crueltie. There making a full point, would ſhe lie gaſping as if ſhe were giuing vp the Ghoſt, till at length hauing gathered winde, ſhee would thus begin to murmur againſt <hi>Fortune.</hi> Vnconſtant dame, ſo much delighting in mutabilitie, as all thy ioye is to alter chances. How wauering is thy wheele, and how vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy fauours, the one ſtill turning, and the other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer remaining long where ſo ere they are beſtowed? Was this the pittie of your heart, to ſet downe ſo vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull a doome, as I ſhould alwaies reſt vnhappie? You whirle your whéele about to pleaſe your ſelfe with the turning, toſſing thereby vnto me one miſerie vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then caſing me of that burthen, to make the next ſéeme more diſpleaſing vnto me, thou ſhewes me my harts ioye, and ſets me on the top of delight to beholde the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwéene weale and woe. But from thence thou throweſt me as quickly downe, as I was ioyfully ſeated, letting thy whéele reſt as ouerlong, while I lie in the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of vnceaſing paine, as it did too too little ſtay at the
<pb facs="tcp:16252:19"/> height of my pleaſure. Thou giues me kinde words, and cruell fare, happie ſightes and horrible heart-akes, thou ſhewes me reſt and ſees me with trouble, ſetting me at the table of daiuties, yet binding my hands leaſt I ſhould touch them, ſo far am I from taſting of their ſweetnes. Vnkinde and vnconſtant fortune, what chance had m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde to be charmed to thy beck, and wherein are we more vnfortunate, then in being forced to obay fortune? To which interrogation, her ſelfe would anſwere with a flat mad fit, curſing her parents that begot her, her birth day wherein ſhee was brought forth, the nurſe that gaue her ſucke, the cradle that lulled her a ſléepe, death for that hee ended not her dayes, and her ſelfe for that ſhe was. Now tearde ſhe her haire from her head, anon ſhe vnapparelled her ſelfe to hir ſmocke, then like a ſpirit would ſhée daunce the Morrice about the chamber, and ſoone ſoſſing her ſelfe downe by the fiers ſide, ſit no les ſenceles then her actions had béen witleſſe, a long time reſting as in a traunce. But at laſt as ouerlate comming to her ſelfe, ſhée would, looking on her ſelfe, ſéeme to bée afraide of her ſelfe, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull to ſée the fruite of her forſaken reaſon, and riſing would ſoone make her readie. Being readie ſhée fell vpon her knées, crying the Gods mercie, and powring forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of teares, in token of her penitencie. And after that being indeede in her righteſt minde: ſhée tooke her lute ſinging to her ſingering this ſonnet.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>WHat booteth loue, that liking wants his ioye?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grieuous that ioy which lackes his hearts-content:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſight of ſweete in taſting of anoy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ads but more griefe to former hearts-torment.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>What ſweet in loue to liue debar'd of loue?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Soure is that ſweete as honny mixt with gall:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Loue with vnreſt the heart to paſsions moue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſighing ſing, and ſinging ſigh withall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16252:19"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>While eyes beholde the pleaſure of my heart</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heart ioyes through eyes in gayning of that ſight:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But when that pleaſure from mine eyes doth part</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heart partes with ioy and reſts in heauie plight.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>And tongue may ſing a hei ho for my heart</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That through mine eyes doth finde both ioy and ſmart.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Which muſick would bée ſo metamorphoſed, as in truth her ſinging would turne to ſighing, and her playing to complaining, when in a rage ſhe would throwe her lute downe, beginning to dilate on her loues vnkindnes, that could be ſo cruell to ſtay foure and twentie houres from her. Now found ſhe fault with her ſelfe for being ſo fond on him that forbeared ſo careleſly her companie, and by and by in a great rage ſwearing to forſake him, ſhe ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her ſelfe to frame a rayling letter for a laſt farewell. But before ſhée had ſcarce written an vnkinde worde, ſhe pauſedon the matter, caſting both pen inke and paper from her, yet vpon her ſecond aduice about ſhe goes with a freſh charge to pen a crabbed charme, and had gone ſo farre as ſhe had ſet downe, <hi>Fie vnkinde wretch.</hi> And there againe in a doubt of going forward or leauing the reſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, ſhée gnawed ſo long vpon her pen in ſtudying what to doe as ſhe had eaten it almoſt quite vp. But at laſt with a reſolution ſhe played the woman, falling into ſo kinde a vaine of ſcoulding, as ſhe had charged him with a thouſand diſcourteſies for miſſing one nights reſorte vnto her. And as ſhe was concluding her colour with a proteſtation, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to deſire to ſée his face againe, in came one of her ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with newes that Maſter <hi>Anthony</hi> was belowe. Which ſo quite purged her of her melancholie, as in a rage ſhe rent the paper, and caſt all her anger with it into the fier, poſting with ſuch haſte to her ſwéete-heart, as in ſtead of running downe ſhe tumbled downe a whole paire of ſtayres. Which bad beginning was careleſly put ouer with the conceiued ioy of his preſence, ſhée entertaining
<pb facs="tcp:16252:20"/> him with a kiſſe, for that he was not forward enough, to beſtowe on her the like fauour. But ere long, ſhée began to perceaue that Maſter <hi>Anthonie</hi> was changed, being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo frolick of his kindnes as hée had béen, and it was no maruel. For ſome reporte of her fore-uſed fondnes was come to his eares, that being no ſmall froſt to my his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer affection; ſo that his onely comming was to make that concluſion ſhe was of late imagining, ſoone finiſhing in wiſe and diſcréet tearmes that her ſuſpect was penning. Vpon whoſe departure, with the paune left of his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, my minion fel into a ſound, there being ſuch a ſtirre for her recouerie, as what for running for <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting for ale, plying warme cloathes and ſuch like, there was no leſſe rule then is in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auerne of great reſorte. Here forſooth, ſaith ſhe that had the <hi>aqua come quickly,</hi> By and by anſwered ſhée, being called that went for the ale, the reſt no otherwiſe replying to euery queſtion and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde. Well at length life was got in her, though no words could bée drawne from her, but being got to bed, ſhe ſong ere long like a bird of Bedlam.</p>
            <p>In which fit I left her, more pittying her péeuiſhnes then her paſſions, the rather leſſe regarding either for that I knew that violent fit would not ſtay long. But to tell you what <hi>Honeſtie</hi> thought all this while, for I knowe that is your longing, and if you be ſhrowe any body, blame her for not letting you haue your will ſooner, by kéeping me ſo long there againſt my will. For vnwilling I was to ſtay there ſo long, and as loath to leaue her before ſhée had left at a full point. That you might know all was my wiſh, and ſince I haue mine now, you ſhall not bée long without your wil. She neuer ſighed hartely, but I laught as merely, being as often readie to piſſe my bréeche for ioye, as ſhe was to ſhed teares, which came from her as had at commandement. And wherefore was <hi>Honeſtie</hi> thus vncharitable thinke you, reioycing at his neighbours mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie? Surely becauſe her ſelfe was ſo fooliſh to bée ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietly moued with nut-ſhels: would it not haue made a
<pb facs="tcp:16252:20"/> horſe breake his halter, to ſée her mumble to her ſelfe as an ape mowes at his own ſhaddow. Doubtles, may I ſpeake it without the ſuſpect of arrogancy, <hi>Honeſtie</hi> hath as much holde of his ciuilitie, as a mare hath of her honeſtie, and yet I might as well be hanged, as be kept from being merry when ſhe mourned. A Camelion cannot change her ſelfe into more kinde of colours then ſhée would vſe change of motions. Sometimes ſhée would walke with her hands claſped and her eyes caſt vp to heauen, as if ſhée were ſent for, with all ſpéede to render an account of her paſſions. Anon ſhe would runne about the chamber like a hare that had loſt her way: then by and by would ſhe houle like a kinde dogge that had loſt her maſter. After that girne like a Monkie that ſées her dinner, and ere long be as dead as a dore naile, lying by the fier ſide as a block doth at the backe of a chimney. And this laſt <hi>ſimile</hi> proues not worſt, for ſhe burned no leſſe through the cinders of too kinde affection, then the logge dooth with the helpe of charke-coles.</p>
            <p>Was not this a monſtrous fit, that had ſo many moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Why if <hi>Honeſtie</hi> ſhould tell you how ſhée would ſometimes bite of her owne nailes, knocking the wall with her féete, praunſing on the ground, and lepping of and on the bed, you would thinke hée had to doe with an vnruly iade. Fie no ſhe was a mankinde creature, and I would not offend them for a kingdome: but this <hi>Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> is ſuch a peſtilent ſpie-fault, as he cannot ſée a wench out-ſtart the bounds of modeſtie, but ſtraight he hollowes the ſight of a ſtriker, thinking it vnpoſſible that if ſhée want maidenly behauiour ſhee can haue womanly hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. Well I knowe ſome will ſay hee is a pick thanke, but were not they ſhonne-thankes they would ſpeake bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Honeſties</hi> ſonne. But thus much for <hi>Honeſties</hi> credit, and now againe to my cract-loue, that had crauled ſo farre into affections extremitie, as ſhe had loſt the habit of her cuſtomers curteſie. I went once more of deuotion to ſée her, becauſe I left her in ſo extreame an agonie: and it was
<pb facs="tcp:16252:21"/> within two dayes after. Whome then I found claſped within a new louers pawes, as iocunde with him of mine honeſtie, as euer I ſawe her pleaſant with Maſter <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</hi> And what thought <hi>Honeſtie</hi> then thinke you? in faith no otherwiſe then I am aſſured you doe now. I thought vpon ſuch fondnes, the prouer be was builded, hot loue wil be ſoone colde, but enough of that in another place, and thus much more of her at this time.</p>
            <p>She was as glad I warrant you of a louer, as a weried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade is of a faire way, and he being tyred is not more glad of a ſtable, then ſhe was deſirous of a bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll: it is onely, for rime at this inſtant, and therefore let it paſſe (I pray you) with your fauour; but whether it doth or no, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhrewe my name if I get any blame. For my tongue will not amble out of the trueth, though I ſhould digge out my guttes with the Spurre, Beware leaſt you offend. There is one ſtill at mine elbowe, and ſayes I muſt take heede how I diffemble, ſince <hi>Honeſtie</hi> is become a deitie. I would I were not, or went not ſo vnuiſible, for then I ſhould not craule ſo eaſily into maydens chambers, and heare them boaſte of ſo many fauours beſtowed by them on this day, ſo many kiſſes giuen to one, another vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her garter, yea and ſhe thought hee went not high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Well but that I am mercifull, and will not name you that are ſo immodeſt as to boaſt of ſuch lightnes, for if I ſhould, I ſhould quite fray away many of M. <hi>Anthonies</hi> companions, from beſtowing them affections on ſo liberall whipſters. But I ſaye no more for ſhame, hoping I ſhall haue no cauſe to ſpeake of the like againe, you will become ſo ciuill, then thus much for you, and now to another.</p>
            <p>This way a coy dame whoſe nice ſtrangenes moued me not to the leaſt admiration: ſhe ſtoode iuſt at the doore, to whom not ſo few as twenty had in my veine made ſuite. They were of ſundrie ſciences, and of all degrées that had tooke the deniall of her, which made mee the rather to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the cauſe, and to obtaine my longing, I lodged my
<pb facs="tcp:16252:21"/> ſelfe that night vnder her bed. When ſhe was layed, and one of her mothers maides with her, ſhee began thus to parly. Wot you what <hi>Nan</hi> (quoth ſhe) how many ſutors thinkes thou haue I ſent packing to daye? Not ſo many (anſwered the maide) as you did the laſt time you were there. Yes faith girle double (replied ſhe.) And found you ſo many faultes in theſe (quoth <hi>Nan)</hi> as you did in the other? Nay I trow wench (anſwered ſhe) I let not them paſſe in whom I diſcouer not many ouer-ſtippes. And what were their faults I pray you, quoth the girle? Some of them had ſtore of wealth (anſwered ſhe) but little honeſtie, other were honeſt enough, but too too hard fauoured; ſome had good faces, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d bodies; other being proper, had crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed countenances, ſome were amiable for fauour, perfect of bodie, yet ill legged; other which were well legde, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with their féete or were ſplafooted; and to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> briefe, they that trode right were either clouterly caulfed, trée like ſet, ſpindle ſhankte, or bakerly knéed; onely there were two e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quiſitely ſhapte, whereof one was too tall, and the other too too lowe. Thus much for their parts, and now to their properties.</p>
            <p>They that were wealthy were meanely qualited, and they that had many good properties were moniles: ſome had good toungs and ſpake well, hauing as ill geſtures, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were rich and ſéemed wiſe, thoſe I ſuſpected to be wenchers. And to make as ſhorte woorke in telling thée of them, as I made ſpéedie haſte in ſending them packing; either I miſlikte their eſtates, ſcorned their perſonages, lothed their want of qualities, or could not away with their kinde of wooing. But ſhal I be ſo bolde (quoth <hi>Nan)</hi> to aſke you one more queſtion? I twentie and thou wilt, for in faith I haue no liſt to ſléepe. In ſooth forſooth, then (quoth the girle) what manner of man ſhall he be, with whom you will match? Mary ſuch a one (anſwered ſhe) as ſhalbe the onely matchles creature in the worlde. But how will you méete with him replyed <hi>Nan?</hi> As he ſhall light vpon me by Fortune. But Fortune is blinde (quoth
<pb facs="tcp:16252:22"/> the wench) and may lead him to another in ſteade of you. Yet as ſhe is blinde (replyed the other) ſo is ſhe a Goddeſſe a good ſupporter of my chaunces, and I know my reporte is ſet ſo néere her elbowe, as ſhe cannot forget me if ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would.</p>
            <p>I marry ſirs you talk of a wench, and what w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s this of a proud one? is it not great pittie but nature ſhould haue compaſſion on this neate creature, and ſhape for her a mirrour of meane worth? Now of my troth <hi>Honeſtie</hi> likes ſuch an one, and why thinke you? I will tell you my reaſon, and if it iumpes with your conceite, ſay you mette with a kill Crowe. I am aſſured that they that are of my minde ſhall eſcape a great deale of trouble, for of mine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, if I ſhould light on ſuch an one, I know certainely I ſhould be quickly rid of a néere nuſhap, in being preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of matching with a nice ninnte, by a nice body: for not being the paragon of the worlde, would kéepe me from marrying with the onely paltrie one of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> worlde: whether then thinke you ſuch to be profitable members of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth? Howſoeuer you think, <hi>Honeſtie</hi> hath ſaid, he thinks them hurtfull to none that eſcape the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> their folly one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y hurtes themſelues, dooing good to others, in the like manner as he hath tolde you. Trot you and you will to trye your Fortune, and runne to wooe ſuch curious cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers, but ſay I bid you take héede, leaſt you reſiſt good lucke, by being importunate to wooe them, with whome you ſhall winne a maſſe of manner-les Monkiſh trickes. And I ſpeak eſpecially to you, that hunt after monſters of modeſtie, deſiring to haue the maidens you would matche with, as very matrones as your mothers. Beware you light not vpon an ouer wearied conceipted ſollom-bird, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one that hath béene ſo curious to be talkte with of any as hauing liued ouer long without one, is become glad of any. <hi>Honeſtie</hi> knowes ſuch, and you may be troubled with ſuch, and how can you thinke your ſelues vnworthie? In faith ill conceited birds, if you thinke your ſelues ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as you are vnable to gouern a wilde wench, you will
<pb facs="tcp:16252:22"/> ſhewe your ſelues more fooliſh, if you match with a nice no-maide. But what ſaide <hi>Honeſtie?</hi> be there any ſuch? I that there are, ordained for the nonce, to nurture ſuch nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. It is as eaſie to be miſlead by hypocriſie, as it is follie to truſt to an vncertaintie, and it is more vncertaine to know now a daies whether a woman bee honeſtly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, or knauiſhly coye, then whether a Smithféelde horſe will proue good, or iadiſh.</p>
            <p>Sée how I haue a tale by the end of a ninnie of my now handled maidens qualitie, which was a Miſers Daughter in the low Countries. Who was ſo proper a péece of fleſh, as I can tell you we haue not many Oyſter women that out goes her in hooke ſhoulders. By reporte ſhe was a louely one, but that ſhe was monſtrous blobber lipt, and ſtoopt ſomewhat vnreaſonably in the vpper parte of her backſide, but that is no matter, her father was richer then moſt in that Countrie, and why ſhould not ſhe thinke her ſelfe the propereſt of a thouſand? of <hi>Honeſties</hi> word ſo by likelyhoode ſhe did, and if you ſay not ſo anon, then ſay I haue heard a lye. She thought her ſelfe ſo proper, as none vnder a Burges his eldeſt Sonne might ſue vnto her, and he too to be no faultie gallant; for he with all commers ſhould be ſo ſurely ſifted by her, to ſée whether they trod their ſhooes aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y or no, as the Miller doth the griſt before he mingles chalke amongſt it. She would haue a fling at their heades, to ſée whether they were round like a ball, or long like a bottell, and ſo from euery parte, til ſhe were paſt the vndermoſt parte of their Pantoples. And in all of them ſhe would be ſure to finde ſome fault or other, the leaſt being a ſufficient cauſe to cut off their procéedings. Thus dealt ſhe ſo long, as at laſt her doultiſh age was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares come vpon her, making her fuſtie curioſitie a ſhamefull mockerie throughout the Countrie; ſo that the generall reporte of her bruted ignomynie made her growe glad of any companie: and now faine would ſhe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> married, though loth to encreaſe her ſhame by matching with farre worſe then ſhe had refuſed being offered, and
<pb facs="tcp:16252:23"/> therefore thinking to hinder the make-ſpéede of murmured ignominie, with a craftie colour of a continuing care to couple her ſelfe to one of Fortunes darlings, ſhe concluded there ſhould be a Lotterie, and whoſe chaunce it was to be drawen by her ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld onely poſſeſſe her w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thered ſelf. You muſt thinke that many were glad to win her, for whom almoſt will not wealth wooe to a bad bargaine? My ſtorie reportes that of all ſortes, ſome for paſtime and others for profite, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut their ſcrolles into fortunes budget, and on the day when my minions draft ſhould be manifeſted, who ſhould haue her by lot, but ſuch an one as <hi>Tom-witles</hi> is, that will cry if one offer to take away his bable.</p>
            <p>A ſutable mate for ſo long a ſearch; there was but one grand foole in a Country, and ſée how Fortune had kept her for him. Now ſuch chaunce follow like curious coye wenches, and may neuer wiſer perſons match with them. And are they not thinke you the méeteſt for them? For they deſire to haue them, that haue the ſmalleſt faults, and <hi>Honeſtie</hi> thinks it y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> leaſt fault in a man to be a foole. Who is more proude then a foole, and what woman more coy for the moſt parte then ſhe that hath leaſt reaſon for it? The Crow likes her own birde beſt, though it be the blackeſt, and would not we haue women thinke well of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues? I pray you let them haue their willes, or they will whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will or no; and if you like them not you may leaue them, and with as good reaſon as they will be ſure to deale ſo with you, vnleſſe you highly pleaſe them. The Aſſe hath a curious eye, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> makes his pace ſo ſlowe; for ſhort legges will trippe at euery ſtone, and what, ſhe is not afraide to fall on a ſtone? And reaſon too, but they will neuer be happie, vntill Tom foole and his fellowes be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht for throwing ſtones at them which often hurt their bellies, whereas their falling breakes but their knées. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las poore aſſes that your eyes cannot kéepe you from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, as they make you ouer-leape often vnknowne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amondes. But what are more pretious then pleaſing thoughts, and what fancies are more full of pleaſure then
<pb facs="tcp:16252:23"/> thoſe that moſt extoll our ſelues. This arrogancie is an infectious peſtilence; for we get pride one from an other, as we purchaſe the plague in a mortalitie. But once more returne we to the merry talke of our coye Maiden.</p>
            <p>After a long progreſſe paſſed in deſcription of the ſwéet hart ſhe would haue, being ſuch an exquiſite proper quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Squire, as is ſcarſe one in a whole Countrey, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> maid ſell with her to this point: Now of my troth (quoth ſhe) by your leaue I am not of your minde, for ſuch a matchles fellowe is as méete a baite to entice many women to doo his wife wrong, as a faire woman ſhall haue ſutors to doo her Huſband a ſhrewde turne. And therefore as I would not wiſh to be matcht with ſuch a crabbed péece of fleſh as none can fancie, ſo deſire not I to holde a mark for euery one to ſhoote at, the rather for that there are fewe men which will refuſe a kinde offer. Beware when the woman wooes, if ſhe be perceiued to be forward to ſome diſpoſitions, ſhe ſhall not want the offering of a bob: ſo that the bobbing bable ſhall bob the foole with her own cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious choice. Which knauiſh quip did ſo nip my Miſtres Daughter on the head, as in troth ſhe left arguing and fell harde to ſcolding.</p>
            <p>This is bobbing with a witnes thought <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> but ſurely it were pittie it ſhould not be true in ſome caſes, and in thoſe onely would I wiſh it true, that ſtriue ſo far to out-goe their fellowes in ſuperexcellent obiectes.</p>
            <p>Beware the Foxe that hath the ſmootheſt ſkinne, it is ſigne his coate is olde, and his wit not young, he will be ſure of a gooſe in ſtore, when many of his neighbours ſhall want one. I know ſome, about whome Nature hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed ſo long time in ſhaping faire faces with proper bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as ſhe hath at laſt for haſte béene conſtrained to let them paſſe with vnperfect hartes. She muſt performe her ſtinte, and a time is limited her to faſhion euery childe; by reaſon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they muſt haue the pureſt harts, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haue the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>keſt ſhapes. I know what you will ſay, and therby wil onely ſéeme to gainſay <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> for that it is a Prouerbe,
<pb facs="tcp:16252:24"/> 
               <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooked without, and crabbed within.</hi> Of tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th I muſt confeſſe, that it is very likely, though not alwaies true, (for no work-man but hath ſometimes a miſchaunce hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to his moſt curious worke, after the finiſhing therof, either by a fall or ſuch like caſuall chaunce) that a halting bodie hath a diſſembling hart, and a miſhapen creature a crabbed diſpoſition, and we doe finde it commonly, that vnder fouleſt aſpects are hidden the faireſt harts, though I know women accompt blacke thinges to be of leaſt worth. But ſearch againe and looke what dye is more perfect, or what will take ſoile ſooner then the milke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like white? well, the maidens propoſition pleaſed <hi>Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> ouerwell, as you may geſſe by my long ſtay vpon it, but I will aſſure you it diſpleaſed no les my yong miſtres. Alas it is a little thing that will not diſpleaſe them whom nothing can pleaſe, and ſhall we thinke a wench could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly pleaſe her long, vnto whom ſo many men were diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king? Now ſurely he ſhall haue a new accompte, that rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons on leſſe then this: namelye, that his matching with ſuch a minion, which was ſo curious to be pleaſed, will craue as great care to be kept pleaſed, as a iade will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire arte to be kept from tiring. Nor doo I ſay ſhe wil be tired, I would rather be driuen to affirme he ſhalbe iaded, though with ſuch an one as will neuer be tired.</p>
            <p>But let ſuch as my Miſtres Many-miſlike is, take héede leaſt by their coye kindenes, they kill their harts whome they would gladly ſaue after, with all their arte, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. How eaſie is it to put that away with our little ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which we would willingly recouer againe with both our hands? I haue knowen ſome Faulkoners that haue béene ſo curious in dieting their Hawkes, as a nice curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan is of her fare, and yet ſometimes they haue ſearcht a whole day after the killing of a carrion Crowe, and miſt of it too. The faire laſtes not alwaies, and ſuch as lightly regarde a good bargaine when it is proffered, may trie the market a twelue moneth after and miſſe of the like offer. The rolling ſtone gathers no moſſe, nor the running fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb facs="tcp:16252:24"/> is worth the catching. They ſhalbe ſure to méete with a fickle hart, that match with ſuch a wauering loue, and an vnconſtant affection is better loſt then found. And for that I am entred into the path of vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie, I wil come to a ſeauenth enemie, which a couple harboured that ſtood behinde the doore.</p>
            <p>He was a Prentice that had foure yéers to ſerue, which I certainely vnderſtoode afterwards, though at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant I geſte no leſſe by his fearefulnes to be ſéene: wel, theſe had ſo wooed and wonne the one the other, as ſure they were, hauing remained ſo by the ſpace of thrée yéers: yet now there was diſlike growen betwéene them, firſte ſpringing from the woman that was diſcontented that ſhe had alreadie loſt ſo much time, being yet bound to endure a longer ſtay. Who knowes not the certaintie of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption confirmed by an order of the Cittie of London, (which is, that if any man ſtanding bound for the ſeruing of yéeres, entangle himſelfe and marrie before the tearme of his yéeres ended, he ſhall double his prentiſhip) and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt ſhe either out-ſtay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or binde him by the haſtie match to ſeauen yéers more ſeruice. Vpon this inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience miſlike harboured in her boſome, hauing tied that with her toung which ſhe could not looſe with her hands; ſo that mad melancholly ſhe was for the matche made by her ſelfe, that tooke ſo ſmall delight therein.</p>
            <p>Now I would all might be ſerued with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame ſauce, thought <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> that ſo ſoone tying themſelues, deſire as ſoone to be looſed: and it is great maruell when it falles out otherwiſe, eſpecially in theſe daies, wherin conſtancie is made a hackney. <hi>Lingring loue breedes miſlike,</hi> and how can that loue be faithfull, that is faſtned with ſo ſlender a thong. There is a thing which maintaines the coherence of two harts, which if it be long wanting, our loue will proue but watriſh affection: I meane that certaintie of an euerlaſting happines, with an aſſurance of a continuall earthly pleaſure. There comes many faire Horſes into Smith féelde in a twelue moneth, which make many that
<pb facs="tcp:16252:25"/> are ſped alreadye, to wiſh themſelues vnprouided, to deale with them; for all men haue not kéeping for two Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. It is time that makes a iade knowen, and our knowledge y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wiſhes him further from vs. Many thinges muſt alter in ſeauen yéeres, for that wonders happen in a moment. In one day a begger and a King are made equal, both the pompe of the one, and the poore eſtate of the other being buried in duſt. Loſſes come ſooneſt vnlooked for, and the worſt bargaines are gotten with the greateſt ſearch: néede raiſeth the market, and much enquirie after a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie engenders ſuſpect there is ſcarcitie thereof. What cannot golde doo, and may it not then eaſily conuert a hart that longes after it? There are many entiſing baites that change many mindes, &amp; who wil not ſtriue for the golden Apple? onely except thoſe that know they cannot get it, though they are deſeruing thereof, which impoſſibilitie muſt néeds hatche miſerie. How be cormorants more pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, then by a diſappointment of their purpoſe? They that foreſtall markets, make often times but bad bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines, as well as the ſluggard that comes a day after the Faire.</p>
            <p>Is it not folly to ſtriue to kéepe a wet Eele by the taile? or what commoditie ariſeth, of holding the Diuell by the great toe? the one is ouer-quick, and the other won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous ſtrong: and in <hi>Honeſties</hi> iudgement a knowne loſſe, the ſooner it comes the leſſe it gréeues, and better it is to be without company, then to be matcht with an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. Slipperie ware is not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beſt Marchandize, and what requires more care, then Glaſſe that is moſt brittle? I know you wil ſay a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hart is as te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I think no leſſe. Then ſince we muſt hazard our welfare, that are conſtrained to deale with ſuch pure metall, being tied to that traffique, let vs not beſtowe all our hope on a péec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we know muſt ſtay ſo long by vs, before we can make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thereof. <hi>Honeſtie</hi> is rather a profeſſed ſolicitor for a woman, then a counſeller to a man: but for that both men and women are troubled with the like diſeaſes, let them
<pb facs="tcp:16252:25"/> vſe my plaſter that like beſt of my knowledge. Where loue ſtrikes the bargaine, their liking cannot ſtart backe, but vnles he be bound by his agréement, affection is a fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle fellowe. What ſurer couenant then ſetled loue? But they which reſpect not their worde, will hardly regarde an oathe. Honeſtie is all, for hee is the father of conſtancie, and a fig for that loue which muſt be tied by the lawe. If we foſter a ſnake ſhe will ſting vs by the boſome, and hée that ſues for an enemie, is worthy to haue his pate broken with want of honeſtie. A tedious ſuite makes ritch law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers and léeſing clients, and a deſire to haue all, makes vs often to looſe all.</p>
            <p>I haue heard of a Gentleman, that tied himſelfe to a poore maide after the manner aforeſaide, meaning to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with her after the death of his father, for that hée durſt not doe it while hée liued. Hée maintained her paſſing brauely, running himſelfe greatly into debt, through the large expenſes ſhe laſht out. Which curious and ritch ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth, made many to looke after her, which otherwiſe would not haue thought on her. A blazing ſtarre preſages alteration, as the Aſtronomers holde it, and doubtles a proper woman gayly apparelled, bréeds miracles in mens mindes. A prancing horſe moues wondring, when a ſure nagge onely pleaſeth the rider; ſo while ſhée liued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her birth, few or none regarded hir, but now ſet foorth as readie for ſale, her gallantnes engendred thoughts of ſome great portion, to be fallen by an vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for accident. Nor will friends let to ſpeake, to make a friend ſpéede well, and hire of the ſame minde gaue forth, that it was ſo indéede; vpon which reporte many wooers were drawne to trie their fortunes, and amongſt them a ritch farmers ſome ſet in his foote to hazard his happe. Whome her parents and friends ſo well liked, being his fathers onely childe, as they began to perſwade their daughter to take it while it were offered after this maner. Tut wench (quoth they) while the graſſe growes the ſtéed ſtarues, and as ſoone goes the young ſteare, as the
<pb facs="tcp:16252:26"/> olde ore to the market. Young heads are fickle, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he ſhould play falſe, how ſhould we remedie it? Golde bies lawe now a dayes, and may not a bribe eate vp a ſure title, as wee haue heard a fat hog did a poore mans glaſſe of oyle? He that can giue moſte ſhall be ſure to ſpeed beſt, and you knowe daughter, your father is not able to wage lawe againſt ſo ritch an enemie. Why woman, you haue not ſéene him this fortnight, and how knowe we but he hath a wife in a corner? By our Lady girle, ſuch windefalles happen not often, as is this day put into your mouth. By cock and pie doo as you will, but if you doo refuſe this proffer, we will denie you our bleſſing. Which counſell ſtroke ſo déepe into her conſcience, as it ſent pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all the affection her proteſted loyaltie had promiſed, and turned it ſo to the farmers ſonne, as in ſhort time hée maried with her.</p>
            <p>By that time as my minion had béen married thrée or foure dayes, thither comes poſting my out-ioynted Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, of whoſe ſtarke ſtaring mad diſcontentment vpon the hearing of his willow guift, <hi>Honeſtie</hi> liſts not to ſtand, ſince you can imagine it was great, but what remedie? What wiſe man would ſue for a falſe-hearted begger, or what gaine ſhould be got by the recouerie of a broken pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin? In ſéeking to haue plagued her, he ſhould haue puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed himſelfe, adding but ſhame to the loſſe of a greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and in the ende recouered a flap with a fore tale. Well I pittie him becauſe of his kindnes which was ſo croſſed, but if <hi>Honeſtie</hi> heares of any ſuch kinde aſſes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, he will make as good ſporte thereat, as the boyes doo at the foole of a Morrice. Are they not worthie to lie by the héeles that purchaſe the countertenor with ſo plaine a prickſong? I warrant you it prict and pincht him too, but his father was the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illing to releaſe him, for that he hopte that loſſe had gaind him more wit. <hi>Honeſtie</hi> could tell you of a thouſand that haue béen ſerued after the ſame order, they hauing promiſed to ſtaye one for another, ſome a yeare, others more or leſſe, whereof ſome haue had their
<pb facs="tcp:16252:26"/> hope ſound within a fortnight of their day, and then think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues néereſt to haue their willes, in come takers pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing their noſes quite beſides the ſwéete ſent of their foreſpoken bedfellowes. This can be no ſmall griefe to a kinde conſtant heart, that hath peraduenture refuſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good likely hoods to ſtay for ſuch a light huſwife. He that will thinke himſelfe ſure to a woman, or ſhee that will build on a mans conſtancie, till the pariſh prieſt hath ſaide <hi>God giue yee ioye,</hi> and the brides bed hath borne it firſt nights w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, he is not of <hi>Honeſties</hi> minde, though I wiſh it were otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>It is as good to bee aſſured of the borne, as to bee made ſure to an vnconſtant heart, for they that looke for les ſhall be diſappointed. God forbid <hi>Honeſtie</hi> ſhould ſay it were vnpoſſible, that two may loue conſtantly vnmarried ſeuen yeres, but he may aboue that two ſay, ſuch are ſcarce found in ſeauen ages. Walke but to Weſtminſter, a place in faith where conſtancie is as little vſed, as wit in Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, and yet there (I warrant you) you ſhall haue your head filled with tales of vnconſtant louers. Goe likewiſe to Poules (a path as well haunted with hunters of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, as <hi>Kemps</hi> head is ſometimes peſtered with knauerie) and blame <hi>Honeſtie</hi> if there you heare not outeries of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering wenches. Long lanes and broade ſtreetes, little cottages and manner places, are at this day by report bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred with naught ſo much as with vnconſtant mindes. Whereby what through the ſorrowe, Conſtancies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainte moues and the griefe honeſties broken pate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, it is great pittie wée ſhould not haue many knackes to knowe knaues by, and as many Iigges to gird gariſh girles with. I peticoate laue, is a pocket ful of new faſſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the drift whereof, is that firſt commers ſhould be firſt ſerued: but they meane no commers which enter not the placket. In Shooleane there is one that ſelles running lether, the vertue whereof is maintained with liquor of a careles heart, ſo that hee or ſhee that cannot play light of loue, ſhall not be cuſtomed there. Withdrawe your ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:16252:27"/> to Crooked lane, and of <hi>Honeſties</hi> credite you ſhall finde more traps to catch Rats and Mice there, then conſtant louers in <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordich</hi> Church at midnight.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay? ſince the art of Cony-catching hath foreſtalled good inuention: but fie on the diuell that driues ſuch wits to ſo bad a bargaine, as to be forſt to ſpend their time in no better ſtudies. They haue néed of good intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencers that ſhall intermeddle with trickes of Coning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhifts: for mine own part, I had rather wade to the middle in Loues whirle-poole, then to the anckles in the brooke of vnconſtancie. And yet force perforce, by Loues appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I muſt haue a fling at her followers. Let them flye to the gallowes, for <hi>Honeſtie</hi> that loues her ſo well, and my fling will driue them to a worſe place, vnleſſe they leaue her. Vp hill and downe hill is a very troubleſome labour, but vp the ladder and downe the rope ends many ones miſerie. What ſtéeper way then to the height of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? and how many often poſt vp and down betwéene that and the valley Likings-recantation. I recant now a daies followes Loues héeles like his ſhadowe: it is a hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting crackhalter, and a hurtfull hinderloue, and beſt he ſhall be knowne by his ſtumpe foote. I meane not a miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penledge, but a reſting loue, that either makes ſuch a full poynt in the beginning, as he can goe no further, or els ſtands at a ſtay two or thrée quarters, not knowing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were beſt to goe forwards or backwards. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames are as daungerous as ſtretches: for as many ioynts are out-ſet or crackt by the one, ſo many vncurable hurts are receiued by the other. <hi>Honeſtie</hi> thinkes a ſeuen nights ſpace is too ſhort a time to faſten a true louers knot, but he that out ſtayes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> moneth may learne as much in that time as is néedfull to be knowne. A longer time is pleaſing to them that haue barres to hinder their forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but he that may goe on without hinderances, if hée aimes at a longer reſpite, take it on <hi>Honeſties</hi> word, hée workes but vpon aduantage. They that build their affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon reaſon, are like to remaine moſt conſtant: for
<pb facs="tcp:16252:27"/> where a condition of profite binds the ſutors, there a long day will not likely be broken. But this reaſon craues wiſedome, the experience whereof muſt a waite on Loues followers, the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctiſe being nothing but this, a care in our choyce to maintaine the maine chaunce. That is, that they which haue little, doe fancie none but ſuch as haue ſomewhat, and they that haue nothing, either to match with ſuch as haue enough to ſerue themſelues and others, or els to fit ſtill in the chimney corner. Al muſt meaſure their liking according to the depth of their deſire, to the end they may liue with contentment, which will (I warrant you) nouriſh conſtancie.</p>
            <p>Now followeth another ſort, which are not the leaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Loue hath, being our common courting lads, who take ſuch pleaſure in their pregnant wits, and ſo great glorie in their readie tongues, as a wench cannot péepe forth the doores, but they muſt haue a fling at her beautie. Firſt comes, faire ladie God ſaue you, and then followes, that the ſight of ſuch a blazing Commet makes them ſtand at the gaze, for that ſuch ſights are ſeldome ſéene. After en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues their application, falling from the celeſtiall creatures to their earthly Goddeſſes, extolling their beauties to ſuch a height, as when they can goe no further, hauing forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their way backwards, they fall downe headlong, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the necke of Good reaſon. Then come they to the good parts of their bodies, and from thence to a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall view of their hidden vertues, building vpon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, <hi>A faire face cannot haue a crabbed heart,</hi> though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them find by experience, but crabbed entertainment to procéede from thoſe their celeſtial obiects: yet the moſt, what through their quicke conceipts, falſe proteſtations and vſuall reſorting into their companies, bring many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a fooles paradice, as they harpe on nothing but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. And maruell not, ſéeing we haue many ſo forward wenches, that if a man looke but earneſtly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, they thinke verely, hee is inamoured of their beautie: but ſhal he ſpeake and ſay he loues them? my father, my mother
<pb facs="tcp:16252:28"/> and all my friends muſt be made priuie to his procéedings, for I know he will haue me.</p>
            <p>Alas light hearts that are lead away with euery kinde blaſt: know ye not that our age flowes with fine wits, that muſt borrow their practiſe of ſuch like patients? Doe not many men cheapen that meane not to buy, &amp; think you to want ſuch cuſtomers? How many come into a Faire with neuer a farthing in their purſes, and yet for faſhion ſake will aſke the price of a coſtly péece of worke? Our tongues ſtand vs in little charges for reparations, and ſéeing they weare not, we will not ſpare to wagge them. But this is beſt knowne to you women, whom nature bindes to the greateſt practice, hauing giuen you no other weapon; yet I may tell you, men cannot want that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, eſpecially in their wooing matters. But did many of both kindes vſe it leſſe, both you and they ſhould ſpéede neuer the worſe, for you ſhould miſſe of many fond faithles ſpéeches, and they ſhould march without as many kinde hit home floutes. They ſhould not playing with the fire, be burnt with the flame, and remaine helples through your careles pitie: nor ſhould you be intrapt in the ſnares of their ſmoothe words, decreaſing your glorious beauty by hopeles conceites of obtaining your withed happines.</p>
            <p>Many honeſt mindes taken at their words, are bound to bad bargaines, when on the contrarie part, a crackt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit regardes neither his own reputation or anothers wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. How eaſte is a frée horſe tired, a good edge-toole ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and a kinde heart ſurfeited? Adull iade will rather be ſpurde to death then breake his pace: and with a bad knife we may aſſay to cut any thing, without dooing it much harme, but woe bee vnto that heart, whoſe mildenes makes it ſelfe ſubiect to a counterfeit kindnes. You ſhall ſighe forth your ſorrow, while they ſmile at their good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, they building their aſſurance of being no loſers on your good diſpoſitions, that ſerue for ſtables, to reſt their hopes in: your good natures muſt bée but roumes for hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that neuer knowe their maſters, and your kinde
<pb facs="tcp:16252:28"/> hearts to ſerue for mangers to féede their had conceites. Their trotting ſhall faſten to your heads <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eapes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, the clauſes whereof ſhall bréede thouſand of doubted miſeries and ten thouſands of carefull heartbrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings. Their counterfeit frendſhip ſhall hinder faithfull and louing procéedings, hurting affection by hindring it from it deſarte, with kéeping it from receiuing the due of requitall. That bootles conſtancie ſhall baniſh faithfull loyaltie by crabbed croſſes, and purchaſe to it ſelf, through a haples concluſion a cart-loade of carefull extremities. True-meaning thereby ſhall be deceaued on both ſides, and kind-heartednes plagued with ouer-ſureſet affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Loue ſhal be banded away with the racket of diſſinm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and beaten at laſt into the hazard Deſpaire by his ſporting enemie. What a great loſſe will followe ſuch a chaſe, and how great expence of hearts griefe, muſt enſue ſo ſhroude a game, geſſe you that lie condemned in the like charges? Onely <hi>Honeſtie</hi> pitties ſuch a paſtime that ends with ſo ſmal pleaſure, and wil now come to giue you war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of what he hath ſéene happen in the like caſes of little conſcience.</p>
            <p>There was one of this ſocietie that had ſo courted vp a wench, as through a potion of pleaſure he had giuen her, her belly roſe like a blowne bladder. Belly round ſhe was, ſo that through his craft her credit ſtoode vpon cracking, which ſhe perceauing entreated her phiſition, that as hée had taſted of her curteſie, ſo he would ſaue her honeſtie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that ſhe was with childe as the truth was. Of my faith (quoth he) what care I? You might haue tooke bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heede, you are beſt to make haſte and get a father for it. I hope (anſwered ſhe) you will not ſerue me ſo: are theſe your faire promiſes, and can your vowes bee ſo ſlightly paſſed ouer? Haue you not made loue to me by the ſpace of a quarter, being vſed kindly of mee, and can you finde in your heart thus cruelly to requite my extraordinarie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, putting me to ſhiftes in this extremitie? Is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your profeſſed whot loue ſhould be ſo ſoone cold, or that
<pb facs="tcp:16252:29"/> your large promiſes ſhould turne to ſo little performance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I cannot thinke you being a man can be ſo cruell, as to caſt away a poore maiden. Away beaſt (quoth he) thy perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are as bootles as thy thoughts, and I am aſſured thou art not ſo fooliſh as to build of any thing I haue ſaide, or of that I haue done but as of a ieſt, if thou dooſt, it will be a bad foundation, and with that he flong forth of the dores, leauing my maimed-maide in a bad taking.</p>
            <p>Doe you tearme ſuch dooing ieſting? thought <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> if <hi>Chaucers</hi> iapes were ſuch ieſtes, it was but bad ſporte; well a ſporte it was, though it proued a ſure earneſt, and who knowes not that ſwéete meates craue ſowre ſauce? Her laughing lye-downe, came to ſad riſing-vp a ſhrewde ſporte to turne to ſuch ſorrie p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtime, and if ſuch an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt penny cannot binde a bargaine, nought wil holde the like chapmen but a halier. Now Tiborne and Wapping waite on ſuch for Porters, as poſt to markets, ſo to ieſt with lac'ſt-mutton. If ſaying had béen all, ſhee had béene fooliſh indéede to haue regarded a fooles ſpéeches, but ſéeing he crept ſo farre into credit with her, as he crackt her plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket lace, how could he of conſcience call that ieſting? Doth <hi>Honeſtie</hi> talke of conſcience to <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls</hi> bailiffes, that haue no care of any thing but to ſaue their caſſokes from being his purchaſe? Now fie of all the Beadles of Bridewell, if they ſpare ſuch a ſporter comming vnder their correction, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out double the dole they puniſh one of <hi>Baals</hi> common Prieſts with. I would their blewe coates might fall to be <hi>Hindes</hi> fées, vnleſſe they giue ſuch foure luſtie laſhes at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery kennell and ſtréets corner they paſſe by. Why vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cloake of honeſt ſatiſfaction, to allure an honeſt minde to lewde corruption, is no leſſe thefte then robbing of Churches, onely the Clarkes conſent ſeemes in the one to craue ſome tolleration ouer it doth in the other. Then you will ſay they deſerue both to be hanged, and ſo would <hi>Honeſtie</hi> ſay, but that their chriſtianity merites charitie. But of my troth if <hi>Honeſtie</hi> were a Iuſtice, ſuch as ſue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſelfeſame order, ſhould either marrie with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
<pb facs="tcp:16252:29"/> haue deceiued, or hang without them, my minion going vnpuniſhed for that time in hope of amendment. Loue is a kinde hart, and mariage is a ſwéete baire what then will not ſuch promiſes gaine of a faithfull louer? This ieſting turnes to lingeing loue, when the weakeſt hath ſurfeited in affection. Swéet ſpéeches haue vowed euerlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, and running in the pleaſant meddowe of kindenes it growes luſtie, ſpending the remnant of his wooing to winne vnto ſuch bad fare: courting endes with ſuch a charge, changing profeſſed loue into burning luſt. Loue lookes to be maintained with kindenes, and when he hath got what wordes can affoorde, then falles he to ieſting, which turns contrary to <hi>Chaucers</hi> meaning, to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſatiſfying of a leachers luſt in earneſt. But too too much of this, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were better, and once more returne we to our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncholly lefte mardemaide.</p>
            <p>She poore ſoule ſet ſo lightly by in her fortie wéekes reckoning, ſo thought on her preſent hard hap, as ſhe quite forgot her accompt, wherby now ſhe was in a worſe taki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g then before: for if being put to her othe, ſhe ſhould miſſe of that, his counter othe would make but a ſo ſo end for her, and therefore thus ſhe beſtirred her ſelfe in the matter. She made her caſe knowne to a fréend, and falling downe vpon her knées, entreated him for the paſſion of our Lady to ſtand good helpe vnto her, to draw her mate to marry with her. Who being a very honeſt man y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> had ſome care of her credit, laboured ſo effectually in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> matter, as what through promiſes and a peece of money, he made it a match, ſo that what through a little honeſtie my man was endued with, and a peece of money my maiden was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with, we had a choptlodgicke. Now woe vnto ſuch wooed ſpouſes, if their mates want altogether honeſtie, and they haue no money, and this might haue perchaunce wonne the ſtanding in a white ſhéete without ſo good a maiſter. Take héede girles how you truſt to ſuch helpes, for <hi>Honeſtie</hi> can tell you they are not ordinarie. It is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to finde one ſuch in euery pariſhe through a Countrie,
<pb facs="tcp:16252:30"/> then to finde a honeſt woman in a houſe of Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Hoſpitalitie. Alas how many honeſt mens children come to decay through this practiſe? Talke with any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Virgine, and excepting one amongſt twentie, if they all not agrée that ſuch enticements were the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of their miſerie, neuer beléeue <hi>Honeſtie</hi> for a halfepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Beware if a rich mariage be offered for a rewarde of breache of honeſtie, there are fewe that will not conſent to leacherie with ſuch briberie.</p>
            <p>But the opening of an other wound remaines, with which loue is hurt by his courting enemies, for they which haue beene once deceiued by flatterie, will hardly be drawen to beléeue ſinceritie, whereby the faithfull ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is hindred from his due. The beaten dogge ſhuns the ſtick, the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted patient feares the Pothecaries drugs, the childe that hath béene ſore whipt for a fault, will feare by offending to hazard his bréeche. Who is more warie of his welfare, then he that hath béen in greateſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? and if loue hath béen wounded with a diſſembled affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he will be afraide to enter into an action from whence the like ſorrowe may flowe. What giues greater hope of conſtanice, then vowed loyalty? or what ſéemes ſwéeter then ſugered flatterie? Affection ſpringeth of kinde v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and loue ſettles on a continued ſhewe of profeſſed zeale, which being ſure ſet, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be remoued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out great danger, except wiſedome be a helper. What ſorrowe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brings, and what care diſcontentment harboureth he knowes not? But of the vnceaſing harts-gréefe with the tormenting ſoure-ſauce which ſeaſoneth the deſtruction of entire affection, none can iudge, ſaue thoſe that haue taſted thereof: onely it may be imagined by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> effects that haue followed the like cauſes (as by the vntimely death it hath brought to ſome, a depriuation of their wits to others, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing diſeaſes to many, namely, the gréene ſicknes, the mother, and ſuch like: and laſtly, to ali mad melancholye fits) that they which are fauoured with the leaſt miſhap that comes through want of their longing, are rewarded
<pb facs="tcp:16252:30"/> with the loſſe of a preſent wel-fare, hauing that ſupplyed by a gifte of ſighing heauines. Now after y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fréedome from ſuch a miſchéefe, who will not ſweare to flie from the like danger? And ſince flatterie cannot without dangerous triall be knowen from faithfull fréendſhip, who will not ſhunne both, fearing to miſtake the one for the other? If a kinde hart hath béene deceiued by a crooked knaue, clad in the robes of a courteous louer, ſhe will euer after miſtruſt the habite, for that it is vnpoſſible to know the hart. Who can forbid the Tailor to vſe his arte? and doo you thinke that any one for an aduantage will let to trie his crafte? The Diuell can change himſelfe into any ſhape, and the onely meanes to knowe him (as is ſaide before) is his ſtumpe foote.</p>
            <p>Liking wil not be long a dooing, and loue that followes is but little, whereby he brings no great harme, but al the miſchéefe comes with deſire, which ſwelles the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and predominates ouer loue and liking: he makes the miſ-rule and kéeps the open Chriſtmas, he deſires the ſporte, and main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ines the paſtime, ſo that though he be long in comming, and ſtaies but little in his Lordſhip, yet the remembrance of his iolitie is not forgotten a long time after. He kéepes his cuſtome euery yéere, and a yéere with him is but a ſhort ſpace, ſo that after he comes to his full age, he makes many Chriſtmaſſes: for Deſire is not ſhort liued. It is therefore this lingring loue that dooth all the harme, becauſe by him Deſire is onely begotten. He that beating the market is willing to buye, will not ſtand long a bargaining, when he hath met with his liking, for feare a francker cuſtomer ſteppe betwéene him and his longing: but if he be careles, he will not deale without a good penniworth. Very eaſily then is the miſchéefe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance taken from women, ſéeing a true-meaning ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor may be as quickly diſcerned, as a careles chapman may be perceiued. And how fondly doo they entrude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the néedles hazard of great diſcontent, that will let their loue runne ſo farre without reaſon, as it
<pb facs="tcp:16252:31"/> cannot be called backe without great gréefe at the leaſt. Though a buyer be not able to giue the ſeller his aſking, yet will he be earneſt to haue it at ſuch a price as he doth offer, and although this louing cuſtomer be not of abilitie to anſwere thy fréends expectation, yet ſhall he not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to be poſſeſſed of thée? he is but a watcher for aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages. So that if either his abilitie be ſuch as of himſelfe he can maintaine thée, or be thy poſſibilitie ſo great, as by his good endeuour he may winne a liuing, thy fréends good will by the poſſeſſion of thée, thy affection is too too colde, if thou kéepes him lingring without his longing, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is ſmall, if he be not an vnceaſing ſutor for it.</p>
            <p>And truely in <hi>Honeſties</hi> minde (and pardon me I pray you with whoſe conceipts it iumpes not) thoſe matches ſhall proſper beſt, where lone is rather reſpected then wealth: prouided there be a care had of the likelyhoode of poſſibilitie which muſt come with one of them. But ſhall one that hath nothing ioyne louing iſſue with an other that hath or is like to haue as little, he hauing no meanes to make a liuing, he ſhewes himſelf to be afooliſh follower of repentance, and an vncharitable procurer of an others wretchednes? There are many good wits, that wanting matter to worke on, wade into the triall of dangerous concluſions, which otherwiſe being imployed would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come profitable members of a common wealth. All can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be heires, and many yonger brothers children are but barely left, though they haue had good bringing vp, which nothing hinders their gentrie, onely now a daies it is a barre to their preferment. For men wil ſooner match their daughters with my yong maiſter arich Coblers Sonne, though they be their heires, then with a Gentleman of a good houſe being a yonger Brother. Héerby comes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of a ancient gentilitie, and this y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> making of vpſtart houſes; héerby thoſe that haue had good bringing vp, muſt either goe to plough and carte, being drudges to ſuch drones, or their natures, diſdaining that, and more abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to begge, leade them to lewde practiſes to maintaine
<pb facs="tcp:16252:31"/> the ſtate of their birth. And did you Fathers which are to match your Children, know the hart-breakings many parents (which haue béene of your mindes) haue found by triall, then would the feare of vnciuill behauiour, which ſpringeth by ſucceſſion from their carterly progenitors, turne your gréedie deſire of golden gaine to a ioyfull gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your poſterities happines.</p>
            <p>But fie of couetouſnes that is the roote of all miſchiefe: for men that haue enough to make their Daughters Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, by matching them with houſes of no ſmall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, will, with the deſire they haue therevnto, wooe men of great liuing with large offers, to match their ſons and heires with them. Who being drawen therunto, will vſe them their wiues mée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly well during the life time of their owne and wiues Fathers, for that their eſtates are by their great portions better maintained, and their beſt fréends thereby well pleaſed. But let your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters beware after your and their Fathers death (when all hope is taken away of a further gaine, and a ſearch made of their aunceſtors alliance) for then ſeeing the baſenes of your pettigrée, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> noble deſcents of their predeceſſors, that corruption of blood which you with your corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of money hath made, and their Fathers couetouſnes hath purchaſed to their ſucceſſion, will (as for the moſt parte it doth in the like caſes) moue ſuch hartbreakinges, as either quarrelles of diuorcement or ſutes of ſeparation will ſurely followe. When on the contrary parte, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting gentrie, thereby to aduaunce your houſes, you would match the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Gent. yonger brothers (of whom there ought to be leſſe regarde, the chiefe houſe being maintained) your Daughters portions, being the onely maintenance of their eſtates, would be ſo ſtrong a helpe to encreaſe their affection towards your children, with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed happines to their poſterities, as knowing no houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde quarrelles can be without charges, they will be glad to ſtudie to encreaſe the ſwéetenes of vnitie, thereby to continue euerlaſting proſperitie to their following ages.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:32"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Honeſtie</hi> knowes what the fairing-monger will ſaye, when he ſhall heare of one ſo flat againſt his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion touching mariages, not letting to affirme that it is moſt neceſſarie that the conſent of parents ſhould be laſt ſued for, and little regarded in reſpect of loue, eſpeciallye ſéeing his Pamphlet buildes ſo diuinelye on farre-fetcht arguments, to proue the contrarie. Therfore to preuent him, and to prouide againſt the great danger their matches-making procure, <hi>Honeſtie</hi> muſt tell him and aſſure all thoſe that are of his minde, that were the worlde like vnto that wherein <hi>Abraham</hi> liued, or were Fathers of theſe daies of his diſpoſition, his argument drawen from the gift of <hi>Euah</hi> to <hi>Adam</hi> by God and ſuch like might ſéeme to proue ſome thing. But ſéeing theſe times in effect are quite contrary to thoſe, and the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men in our daies, altogether diſagréeing to theirs of that age, his time had béene better ſpent in a worke to ſome other purpoſe. For a little to ſéeme to flie from my matter, and to haue a fling at him; how many Fathers now a daies are there ſo carefull of prouiding conuenient mates for their children at a ſeaſonable time, as our great Grandfather <hi>Abraham</hi> was? Againe, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye haue children that are ſo obedient to bend their loue to their Parents liking as was <hi>Iſaac?</hi> Oh Sir, you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, our yong ones are of riper wits, and far forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then Children were in thoſe daies, and our olde ones are of more couetous mindes and far forwarder to be drawen to their childrens good: for what greater good then to enioye them they loue? and what will offend our parents more then to entreat that? he ſent his ſeruant to ſearch forth one of his next kinne, not to enquire after one that had moſt wealth, and ſhould ſome children entertaine no loue in our time vntill their parents procured it, nor ſue for a match before their fréends made it, it were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite their honeſtie ſhould be great, or I knowe what will follow. Yet againe, Fathers liue not now adaies ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily aboue a hundred yéeres, whereby they haue a long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb facs="tcp:16252:32"/> gouernement ouer their Children, but beholde it is far contrary, and therefore it requires contrary procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. And laſtly, (for that I will not be long at this time in this matter) the holy writ beares not ſuch ſway in our conſciences, as it workt wonders in theirs of thoſe daies, and therefore to helpe our weaknes in the want of that warrant we muſt vſe the meanes, loue, to drawe vs to that euerlaſting happines.</p>
            <p>But once more to my courting companions to make as ſpéedie an end with them, whoſe haire-braine fancying and fickle affection, is no ſmall hindrance to loues procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. <hi>Honeſtie</hi> hauing ſet downe the meanes to finde out their knauerie, hath alſo prouided a batte to beate downe ſuch flatterie, the inſtrument to finde out their diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being a ſearch into their lingring, and the clubbe to match their clubbe féete, a loathing of their company. But to come to the puniſhment I would haue ſuch to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued with, in my opinion, and by <hi>Honeſties</hi> doome, they are worthie to be ſet for ſcarre-crowes in newe ſowen fieldes; and the rather thus goes my iudgement, for that ſéeing they are ſo ſkilfull to doo harme in townes and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, if that bad-uſed wit were forſt to be imployed about that commodious doo-good, they would inuent excellent meanes to preuent the ſpoyle the rauenous birds commit. Their pregnant wits and cunning deuices to catch wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens affections that farre excéede crowes in reaſon and diſcretion, confirme they would be ſtrange, and therefore profitable; yet becauſe it is ſomewhat too bace, though their practiſes are as beaſtly, I will ende with them with this reſolution. That they are as worthie to ſtand in white-ſhéetes in Churches, for leauing women in deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate caſes, hauing drawen them into that fooles paradice of ouer-paſſionate affection, as they that poyſon ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers bellies: This would make faithfull ſutors happie, conſtant louers ioyfull, and conrting diſſemblers feareful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> hauing noted theſe enormities harbored in lewde diſpoſitions ſhuffled into this Morrice, at laſt lent
<pb facs="tcp:16252:33"/> his eares, and beſtowed his eyes, ioyning with him his beſt vnderſtanding to ſearch into the natures of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> remnant, to ſee whether y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> multitud were mixed with theſe in bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits. But behold ſo contrarie practizes were performed by them, as thoſe procéedings are diſagréeing to the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of perfect vnitie. Amongſt theſe did I beholde <hi>Loue</hi> dandled with ſwéete muſick, and conſtant affection vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n with modeſt demeanour. The ſoueraignes of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie diſplayed their heauenly dignitie, by the imperiall colours of matchles beautie, grounde with the <hi>Ambroſian</hi> oyle of celeſtiall courteſie; and the matronly deities pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their ethereall diſcréetnes, in following the heauens preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Loues true imitation. I ſaw Kindenes mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Goodwill, Affection lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vnto Liking, &amp; Loue embraced with Loyaltie, Vertue leading the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eternall happines. They liked not for a moment, loued not vpon aduantage, nor wooed but with a good intention. Theſe ſhaked not hands with hatefull hearts, nor vſed ſmoothe tongues with diſſembling thoughts. They courted not kindely, to corrupt ſhamefully, ne proteſted with vowes, to wound with wordes, and kill with déeds, but hand and heart went together, and the tongue vttered their paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate conceites, their heart louing them as faithfully as their tongue labored to winne their courteſie. And you no earthly creatures, though ioyned with men for their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good, (you heauenly ſaints I meane, maſking in the ſhadowes of terreſtriall ſhapes) you beautifie this crue with your deuine motions, whoſe mindes ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely inrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the true wiſdome that vpholdes Loues welfare. Your ſacred actions, ayde his ſimple followers, &amp; naught but your carefull kindnes binds mens weake affections from vnconſtancie. You make their praiers effectuall, their requeſt gayning through you the ſafetie of their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. Your pittie brings them to pietie, and your almes relieues them from the captiuitie of Deſpaire. Deſtreſſed <hi>Honeſtie</hi> is ſoly harbored within your milke-white bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, and were it not for your bountifull charitie, his end
<pb facs="tcp:16252:33"/> would be tormenting beggerie. Your allablaſter pappes do wholy miniſter moiſture to my conſuming welfare, and from their ſugered teates doe I onely drawe my liquor of life, ſo that by your motherly kindnes to decaying <hi>Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> they reape likewiſe their bliſſe, that would giue mée my baine, recouering contrarie to their wils the remayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their weale. For how marcheth the paſſionate ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier without you ſound the alarome of his good-ſpéede? or how fareth the amorous gallant, except you play the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liard of acceptance? Vnfortunate eyes, your pearcing fightes ſhal be cruelly curſt, and vnnaturall vſage ſhall be offered to your obedient hearts, for ſéeing and adoring ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall obiects, vnles their relenting pittie take mercie on your deſtreſſed abiects. And blaſpheming tongue, thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled impudencie ſhall heape vpon thy owne back a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of vntollerable miſeries, by being forced to vtter exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable ſlaunders againſt them for their hard hearts, that were purchaſed to worke your hard happe through your owne iniurious follie. Paſſions of diſcontent muſt pleaſe your fancies, and ſorrowfull poems muſt grace your mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; déep ſighes muſt ſtraine your heart-ſtrings, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſorrowe lull you a ſléepe, when viſions of new deſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes muſt diſquiet your greateſt happines, and dreames of freſh vexations forbid you the leaſt eaſe. You ſhall ſuc in vaine, becauſe you haue delighted in vanitie, and hope without obtaining, for that your heart haue harbored diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, except theſe goddeſſes, whoſe goodnes is vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, vouchſafe to miniſter a plaſter of pitty to your louing pietie. It is their courteſie that muſt make you chereful, and their good conceits muſt cheriſh your dying mirth; their liking muſt honour your affection, and their grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full kindnes muſt aduance the zeale of your proteſted loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie. It is in their choyſe to change your chance, and in their power to bridle Fortune, for that the Fates, being their ſiſters, are at their calles to ſet downe your deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. If they ſay they doe hate you, beware, for they can hurt you, but if they affirme they loue you, ſtriue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb facs="tcp:16252:34"/> your preſent happines, and feare to loſe the proffered bleſſednes. Why are women accounted weake, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their nature is pure? Or wherefore are they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie but that men cannot liue without their companie? When we are ſuccorles they comfort vs, being melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they chéere vs, and they are the meanes to redéeme vs from the gates of hell. Being mad, their muſicall tongues chaſe away the euill ſpirits, being bewitched their loue charmes the tormenting diuels, and being ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp by the gulfe licentiouſnes, the heauens haue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the helpe to redéeme vs from that helliſh furnace.</p>
            <p>Thus much for their power, &amp; now a little of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties. O ſacred mercie (neuer more honored then in the pittifull boſomes of theſe feminine deities) thou holds thy chief harborow within their paſſionate beſomes, &amp; only art nouriſhed in their relenting harts. Thou ſingſt within the cloſets of their pittifull conſciences, &amp; reioyceſt within the caſtles of their celeſtiall ſoules: thou liueſt with them ſecure, and makes through them multitudes of miſerable wretches poſſeſſors of the higheſt happines. Thou beares the ſighes of ſuing ſwéet-hearts, &amp; comforts the pinching griefe of pining louers. Thou meditates of their vowes, and ſtudies to requite their carefull affection with kindeſt curteſie. Thou pittieſt the fooliſh maladies of fond noui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; ſorroweſt at the weaknes of many mens wiſdome. Thou ſtriueſt to do no wrong, that thou maiſt be frée from iniurie, and labours to ſhunne ſuſpect, that thou maiſt bee without miſdoubt. Thou ſtudieſt to repay that thou maiſt reape thy due, and kéepeſt thy day that thou maiſt bee well dealt with. Yea much more and ſo much the better for man, thou pitties them that would ſpoile thée, and forgiues them that would hurt thée: thou wiſheſt them well that would dereaue thée of thy weale, &amp; loueſt them (which is thy on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fault) ouer entirely that eſtéeme of thy proffered kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes too too careleſly. Yet let diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue the ſecond place with you, for ſhe guides them by reaſon, and that gouerns men with wiſdome. She knowes when to charme with
<pb facs="tcp:16252:34"/> ſwéete melodie, and when to correct with louing perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: ſhe vſeth to dandle vertue, and reproue vice, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace good and flie from euill, and willingly to ſubiect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient imitation to holſome counſell, as alſo dutifully to deſire libertie from ſtooping to iniurious doctrine. Shee ſearcheth into the depth of ſubiected ſeruiſe, and diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whether it be offered of curteſie, or proffered of kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, regards it according to it value, and rewardes it with it full worth. She teacheth to like ere they loue, and louing to encreaſe or deminiſh the heate of their fancie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportion of kinde coales that nouriſheth the fire of their affection. She perſwadeth to launce, cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the bones, to finde out the danger, and ſéeing what likelyhoode either of weale or woe is likeſt to enſue, thée ſheweth them what is good to withdrawe the putrified li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and what is holſome to preſerue the ſound loue. And ſhe ſtudies to make them happie, by wiſhing men their welfare, to make them conſtant, by endeuoring to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe a ſparke of loyaltie, and to make them honored by inſtructing them in the true rules of modeſtie.</p>
            <p>And now ſtep in further thou beautifying modeſtie; for thou addeſt no ſmall renoune to their adored natures, nor doth thy baſhfulnes meanely adorne their highly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed excellencies: thy roſie bluſſhes bring no ſmall honor to their admired beauty, nor euer dies that ſacred ſtayning colour, vntil by mans corruption, that maidenly marke be extinguiſhed. Yet then (but ah that man ſhould do ſo much) thy decent ſobrietie aduanceth the dignity of their woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chaſtitie, and thy matronly behauiour diſplayeth the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraintie of their motherly nurture. Thou giues examples that imitated, preuent occaſions of enticing offers to draw to folly, and eſcapes the iniurious ſlanders of ſuſpitions ſearchers, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hunt after ſhewes of ſenſuality. Thou main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineſt peace at home, eſcapeſt ſuſpect abroade, and keepeſt thy louers heart from harboring ielouſie, the chiefe procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of greateſt miſerie. And thou gaineſt liking and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeſt affection, receiuing loue and loyaltie with an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:16252:35"/> pledge of neuer-dying conſtancie. Neither art thou euerlaſting goddes, a ſtranger to mens-helpers; for thou withall the vertues waite vpon theſe beautiful ſpectacles, and they with the Graces extol thoſe the earths miracles. Their praiſes are vnſpeakeable, for that their worth is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualuable, and their deſartes vnrequited, becauſe through mans weakenes miſpriſed; but ſuch and ſo great were the adorned excellencies of theſe humaine deities, as their practiſes layde open their princely courteſie, and their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances made their louers happie. And men reioyced through their faithfull affection, ſtudying to requite wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens euerlaſting kindnes with the reward of neuer-cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conſtancie. Men vſed heauenly wiſdome to obtaine liking, and carefull behauior, to confirme loue being purchaſed, and women were forward to beſtowe modeſt kindnes, being faithfully dealt withall, and effectually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited proffered curteſie, neither being too too coye, or ſhewing themſelues ouer forward to be wonne. But brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo to end, euery one of them rendred like for like with proofes of neuer-altering affection, they thereby gaining vnto themſelus the ſugred ſwéetnes of cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall amitie, &amp; tying vnto their kinde thoughts, the affections of their well-willers, with euerlaſting conſtancie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16252:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
